<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The unnatural brother a tragedy, as it was acted by His Majesty's servants at the theatre in Little Lincolns-Inn-Fields.</title>
            <author>Filmer, Edward, b. ca. 1657.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1697</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 142 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 31 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B22957</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing F907</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12039535</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12039535</idno>
            <idno type="VID">199141</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B22957)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 199141)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 67:20)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The unnatural brother a tragedy, as it was acted by His Majesty's servants at the theatre in Little Lincolns-Inn-Fields.</title>
                  <author>Filmer, Edward, b. ca. 1657.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 52 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J. Orme, for Richard Wilkin ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1697.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Preface signed: Edw. Filmer.</note>
                  <note>Advertisements: t.p. and p. 52.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Enrique Valdive</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Enrique Valdive</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:199141:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:199141:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE <hi>Vnnatural Brother:</hi> A TRAGEDY.</p>
            <p>As it was Acted by His MAJESTY's Servants, AT THE THEATRE in <hi>Little Lincolns-Inn-Fields.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>J. Orme,</hi> for <hi>Richard Wilkin,</hi> at the <hi>Kings-Head</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s-Church-Yard. MDCXCVII.</p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="publishers_advertisement">
               <body>
                  <head>ADVERTISEMENT.</head>
                  <p>There are lately publiſhed, <hi>Ibrahim</hi> the XIII. Emperor of the <hi>Turks,</hi> A Tragedy, and the <hi>Spaniſh Wives a Farce:</hi> Both Written by Mrs. <hi>Mary Pix.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Younger Brother, Or Amorous Jilt:</hi> Written by Mrs. <hi>A. Behn.</hi> Printed and Sold by <hi>Richard Wellington.</hi>
                  </p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:199141:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:199141:2"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>NOT many daies after the very cold reception which this Play met with on the Stage, as I was walking up and down my Chamber ſomething diſcontented, tho not much mortified neither, at the unkindneſs of the Town, I happened to caſt my eye on a Book which lay in a Window, and that proving to be the firſt Volume of Mr.</hi> Drydens <hi>Plays, I opened it, by meer chance, juſt on a Prologue of his which begins thus,</hi>
            </p>
            <lg>
               <l>Self love (which never rightly underſtood)</l>
               <l>Makes Poets ſtill conclude their Plays are good:</l>
               <l>And malice in all Criticks runs ſo high,</l>
               <l>That for ſmall Errors they whole Plays decry;</l>
               <l>So that to ſee this Fondneſs, and that Spite,</l>
               <l>You'd think that none but Mad-men Judge or Write.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>
               <hi>I was both ſurpriſed and pleaſed with that Chance which had ſo thrown me on thoſe Verſes. For whereas before, I had for ſome time tortured my Brain, to find out thoſe many imperfections which probably might have occaſioned the ill ſucceſs of this Play, I then began to lay aſide ſome part of that care, and to think that the Malice and ill Nature of the Critick, in catching at every little ſlip, and improving of every inconſiderable fault, might perhaps have an equal hand in that misfortune, with the weakneſs or fondneſs of the Poet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>I had no other way to clear this point, and find out the truth of the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, but to employ all the Friends and Acquaintance I had about the Town, to inquire into thoſe objections which were generally made againſt this Play. They did it: and, as I have very good reaſon to believe, gave me a faithful account of all. And yet all, at laſt, came to no more than this: That the Play was too grave for the Age, That I had made choice of too few Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, and that the Stage was never filled; there ſeldom appearing above two at a time, and never above three, till the end and winding up of the whole.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:199141:3"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Theſe are the mighty faults that have ſo intirely Damned this Play: and yet if theſe muſt be thought faults now in our nicer Age, I am ſure they were not thought ſuch heretofore by the Antients; for they generally made uſe of but few Perſons, and never made it any part of their buſineſs to fill the Stage. Nay, we all know that</hi> Horace <hi>lays it down as a Rule.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>—Nec quarta loqui perſona laboret.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>Nor were theſe thought faults by our more modern Criticks, about Fif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen or twenty years ago, when that excellent Play of the</hi> Orphan <hi>firſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared on the Stage. For that, tho liable to all the very ſame exceptions which hitherto have been made againſt this, yet was received with all the applauſe imaginable. I muſt confeſs, foreſeeing part of what has ſince hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened, and meerly to gratifie the Rabble, after I had finiſhed this Play, I ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded a Comical part to it. Wherein, ſo there were but a ſmart kind of a hurry and confuſion, with a Song or two at the end</hi>
            </p>
            <q>—His nam plebecula gaudet.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>I thought it would have paſſed well enough. But the Comedy being altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther independent from the Tragedy, and the whole appearing ſomething too long the firſt time it was acted, I eaſily conſented to have it all left out, and ſo threw my ſelf wholly on the Men of ſenſe for my Judges.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>Verum Equitis quoque jam migravit ab aure voluptas</l>
               <l>Omnis, ad incertos oculos &amp; gaudia vana.</l>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>For, to my coſt, I find that even our men of Senſe, have been ſo long entertained with the gaudy, glaring ſplendor of our Operas, that nothing now can pleaſe their eyes, but what dazels 'em: And that their ears have, of late, been ſo well belabour'd with Drums, Kettle-Drums, Trumpets, and Hautboys, that they are almoſt become deaf to Senſe, or any thing elſe, convey'd to 'em in a leſs Noiſe, than thoſe their darling-Conſorts generally are. But no more of this—which may ſeem a little tart, and to ſavour ſtrange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of the vanity of a diſcontented Poet, who will be ſure to find out any other reaſon for the miſcarriage of his Play, than that which was perhaps the only true one, I mean the badneſs of it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>But I had almoſt forgot to acquaint the Reader with one objection more, againſt this Play, than what I have yet mentioned. On the third day, there was a certain Lady in one of the Boxes, who thought ſhe could not more ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectually decry it, than by declaring aloud that it was nothing but an old Story taken out of</hi> Caſſandra. <hi>And I readily grant it: yet can by no
<pb facs="tcp:199141:3"/> means allow that to be a fault. Mr.</hi> Dryden <hi>has ſaid too much in the defence of ſuch an innocent piece of theft, and extremely well juſtified the thing, both by his Arguments, and Practice. All I deſire of that Lady, by way of amends, is, that if ever theſe Papers have the happineſs to reach her hands, ſhe would be pleaſed to renew her acquaintance with the ſtory of</hi> Alcinoe <hi>in that Romance, and compare it with this Play: And then I dare be bold to affirm, ſhe will not think me over-much beholding to it: But may perhaps be ſo charitable, as to entertain a more favourable opinion both of the Play, and of the Poet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>I have but one word more to the Reader, and then I ſhall leave him to the Play, either to read it, or let it alone, which he pleaſes: And that is, that he would not charge me with any Errors of the Preſs. The Bookſeller in my abſence, has undertaken the care of inſpecting it, and therefore he only ought to be accountable for all ſuch faults.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>EDW. FILMER.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="prologue">
            <pb facs="tcp:199141:4"/>
            <head>PROLOGUE.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>BLeſs'd were theſe happy daies, if ever any,</l>
               <l>When Poets flow'd with Wit, and you with Money.</l>
               <l>But now, both Wit and Money run ſo low,</l>
               <l>They're at the pooreſt Ebb they e're can know,</l>
               <l>This Clipt, that dwindled into Farce and Show.</l>
               <l>As for our Coin, the Wiſdom of the State,</l>
               <l>May ſtop our ruine and prevent our Fate;</l>
               <l>What will n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t paſs by Tale, may paſs, by Weight.</l>
               <l>But who can our corrupted Wit reſtore,</l>
               <l>And make that Currant as it was before?</l>
               <l>O! could we but with equal Balance ſit,</l>
               <l>And by the niceſt ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ruples weigh out Wit,</l>
               <l>How many pieces good, and fair to ſight,</l>
               <l>Would yet be found by many Grains too light?</l>
               <l>In this great dearth of Wit, our Poet here</l>
               <l>Preſumes to treat you with his Country fare,</l>
               <l>Not that he thinks it better than your own,</l>
               <l>Or what you daily meet with in this Town:</l>
               <l>No, tho a Poet, he is not ſo vain;</l>
               <l>You are to judge, he but to entertain.</l>
               <l>Freedom of Cenſure he to all allows,</l>
               <l>And with ſubmiſſion to your Judgment bows.</l>
               <l>He only hopes you will be pleas'd t' excuſe,</l>
               <l>Small faults in a raw unexperienc'd Muſe,</l>
               <l>Which trembling comes, full of ſad frights and fears,</l>
               <l>And almoſt naked on the Stage appears,</l>
               <l>No Paint, no Patches, to adorn her brow,</l>
               <l>That is</l>
               <l>No thundering Conſort, nor no glareing ſhow;</l>
               <l>Thoſe pretty knacks, ſo much of late in uſe,</l>
               <l>To varniſh, and ſet off a homely Muſe.</l>
               <l>Good, eaſie ſenſe, our Poet bad me ſay,</l>
               <l>Is all that he has aim'd at in this Play;</l>
               <l>Well too, he thinks, if he that mark has hit,</l>
               <l>Since the beſt Senſe, is ever the beſt Wit.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="epilogue">
            <pb facs="tcp:199141:4"/>
            <head>EPILOGUE.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>THE Poet, with the Soldier ſhares this fate,</l>
               <l>Courting your favour, he incurrs your hate.</l>
               <l>Tho one does for your daily pleaſure write,</l>
               <l>The other, for your darling int'reſt fight,</l>
               <l>Yet equally unkind, you both do ſlight</l>
               <l>The Man of War forſooth's too rough, unfit</l>
               <l>For civil Company; The Man of Wit,</l>
               <l>A meer pretending Fop, a ſcribling Tool,</l>
               <l>Made up of Madman half, and half, of Fool.</l>
               <l>What is it then, that thus in ev'ry age,</l>
               <l>Draws one toth field, the other to the Stage?</l>
               <l>No hope of Fame or Profit ſure, for they</l>
               <l>In this too like, their harder Stars obey,</l>
               <l>Both drudge for little Honour, and leſs Pay.</l>
               <l>What e're it is provokes 'em, yet we ſee,</l>
               <l>Each fondly courts his unkind deſtiny;</l>
               <l>For as the gen'rous Warriour, void of fear,</l>
               <l>Preſſes on danger ſtill as it draws near,</l>
               <l>And tho he ſees thouſands before him fall,</l>
               <l>Yet briskly ventures on, and flings at all:</l>
               <l>The Poet ſo, tho daily on the Stage,</l>
               <l>He ſees the dire effects o'th' Criticks rage,</l>
               <l>Yet fearleſs dares thoſe doughty foes engage.</l>
               <l>And one's no ſooner fairly down, but ſtrait</l>
               <l>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>p perks another, careleſs of his fate.</l>
               <l>As for the Poet of this preſent night,</l>
               <l>Who ſpite of all diſcouragement dares write,</l>
               <l>He neither fears nor does the danger ſlight.</l>
               <l>If you reſolve to kill, he ſays you may,</l>
               <l>He only begs a very ſhort delay,</l>
               <l>Come all again, and maul him,—the third day: </l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="dramatis_personae">
            <pb facs="tcp:199141:5"/>
            <head>The Perſons repreſented,</head>
            <list>
               <head>MEN.</head>
               <label>Beaufort</label>
               <item>Governour of <hi>Lyons.</hi>
               </item>
               <label>Grammount</label>
               <item>Nephew to the Governour.</item>
               <label>Dampierre</label>
               <item>Brother to <hi>Grammount.</hi>
               </item>
               <label>Montigny</label>
               <item>Friend to <hi>Grammount.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>WOMEN.</head>
               <label>Elvira</label>
               <item>Wife to <hi>Grammount.</hi>
               </item>
               <label>Leonora</label>
               <item>Siſter to <hi>Grammount.</hi>
               </item>
               <label>Lyſette</label>
               <item>Woman to <hi>Elivira.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>A Page and other Attendants.</p>
            <p>The Scene is a Caſtle about a League di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance from <hi>Lyons</hi> in <hi>France.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="act">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:199141:5"/>
            <head>ACT I. SCENE I.</head>
            <stage>
               <hi>Enter</hi> Beaufort <hi>and</hi> Dampierre.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Beau.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>NO more: thou haſt wrought a ſecret from my Breaſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </l>
                  <l>Which may in time prove fatal to us both.</l>
                  <l>For now methinks I do begin to hate</l>
                  <l>Thee, <hi>Dampierre,</hi> as the only Man on Earth</l>
                  <l>Who has it in his power to check, and blaſt</l>
                  <l>Thoſe Glories, now in my declining years,</l>
                  <l>Which I ſo juſtly purchaſt in my Youth!</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Damp.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>The languiſhing ſick Man, without reſerve,</l>
                  <l>Freely lays open his Infirmities,</l>
                  <l>To his Phyſicians kill in hopes of Cure:</l>
                  <l>The hearty Penitent, then only meets</l>
                  <l>With true and real comfort, when he dares</l>
                  <l>Unload his o'ercharged Conſcience, and expoſe</l>
                  <l>His niceſt Scruples to the pious <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>re</l>
                  <l>Of ſome grave Ghoſtly Father.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Beauf.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Ah <hi>Dampierre!</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Could I with the good Penitent Confeſs,</l>
                  <l>And at the ſame time quit the darling Sin;</l>
                  <l>Or with the afflicted Patient hope for eaſe</l>
                  <l>Of all my pains, by telling my Diſeaſe,</l>
                  <l>I then were truly happy<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> But alaſs!</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Elvira</hi>'s not ſo fair, as ſhe is good:</l>
                  <l>The ſhining luſtre: of her ver<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uous mind,</l>
                  <l>By far ſurpaſſes that of her bright Eyes.</l>
                  <l>Thoſe Eyes, which yet dart beams reſiſtleſs</l>
                  <l>As the Sun in his full Noon tide Glory,</l>
                  <l>Beams, which ſtrike me blind to vertue<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> honour,</l>
                  <l>And indeed to all things elſe but love. Oh—</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Damp.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Reflect not ſo ſeverely on your faults,</l>
                  <l>I do beſeech you, Sir, but as a man,</l>
                  <l>Allow ſome grains for humane frailty.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:199141:6"/>
               <speaker>Beauf.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Have I, in my great Maſters ſervice ſpent</l>
                  <l>Full Forty years, and won renown enough</l>
                  <l>To glut the moſt ambitious Hero's hopes?</l>
                  <l>Have I paſs'd o'er the boyling heats of youth</l>
                  <l>With an untainted reputation?</l>
                  <l>And ſhall I now, now in my riper years,</l>
                  <l>Stain all the glories of my former life?</l>
                  <l>No, <hi>Dampierre,</hi> no, it cannot, muſt not be.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Damp.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Do you in earneſt love <hi>Elvira,</hi> Sir?</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Beauf.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Love her! does the devout Recluſe that has</l>
                  <l>Renounced this world aſpire to Heaven?</l>
                  <l>Does the Ambitious Hero covet Fame?</l>
                  <l>Or the old Miſer doat on hoarded Gold?</l>
                  <l>Love her! By Heaven, I ne'r lov'd glory</l>
                  <l>Half ſo well, nor ſo much dreaded the ſucceſs</l>
                  <l>Of doubtful War, as now I do of Love.</l>
                  <l>Fearleſs, I have a thouſand times outbrav'd</l>
                  <l>The greateſt dangers, and outfac'd grim Death</l>
                  <l>In the moſt ugly ſhape that War could ſhew it;</l>
                  <l>Yet now want courage to encounter</l>
                  <l>Her fair Eyes, and like an arrant Coward,</l>
                  <l>Tremble and quake at her approach for fear.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Damp.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>For fear of what, Sir, of a Woman?</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Elvira</hi> is no more, no more than a</l>
                  <l>Meer Woman; an imperfect piece of Man,</l>
                  <l>Made only for his Pleaſure.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Beauf.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Hah! by Heaven</l>
                  <l>She's Natures Maſter piece, ſhe's all Divine,</l>
                  <l>Fair as an Angel, Virtuous as a Saint.</l>
                  <l>But why, alas! do I ſo much as name</l>
                  <l>Her hated Vertue: Would ſhe were a VVhore,</l>
                  <l>A Common Proſtitute, ſince ſhe is Married:</l>
                  <l>Or rather ſince ſhe is Married to <hi>Grammount,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>O! let me wiſh her Dead, laid in the Grave,</l>
                  <l>And hoarded up l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ke ſome old miſers VVealth,</l>
                  <l>In the dark intralls of the happy Earth,</l>
                  <l>VVhere none the mighty Treaſure could enjoy,</l>
                  <l>Since I cannot.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Damp.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Nay, now, Sir, I could chide.</l>
                  <l>VViſh not <hi>Elvira</hi> Dead, but think her ſtill</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:199141:6"/>
                  <l>Amongſt the living wonders of the Age,</l>
                  <l>The faireſt much of her bewitching Sex.</l>
                  <l>VVho, tho ſhe may have charms enough to kill,</l>
                  <l>Yet may too entertain ſome ſoft deſires,</l>
                  <l>To cure the wounds her fatal Beauty gives:</l>
                  <l>And therefore, Sir, you ought at leaſt to hope.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Beauf.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>It is to innocent deſires alone,</l>
                  <l>That hope dares ſhew a comfortable end;</l>
                  <l>But mine are guilty all: How then can hope</l>
                  <l>Pretend to flatter him, who were he bleſt</l>
                  <l>In all the joys ſucceſsful Love can give</l>
                  <l>Muſt yet be wretched, miſerable ſtill,</l>
                  <l>Torn with the pains of a too late remorſe,</l>
                  <l>Sharper than thoſe of diſappointed love.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Damp.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Theſe, Sir, are odd phantaſtick notions</l>
                  <l>Of a working brain, fitter for Schools</l>
                  <l>Than for a Lovers care, whoſe Miſtriſs is his all.</l>
                  <l>He who dares rifle the induſtrious Bee,</l>
                  <l>Snatches the Honey careleſs of the Sting:</l>
                  <l>And he who briskly plucks the bluſhing Roſe,</l>
                  <l>Laughs at thoſe Thorns that would revenge the Rape.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Beauf.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>How powerful do thy arguments appear,</l>
                  <l>To a mind wholly prepoſſeſſed with love!</l>
                  <l>Thou art a Maſter, ſure, in that ſoft art,</l>
                  <l>And may'ſt aſſiſt me: I alas! am rough,</l>
                  <l>Grown old in Camps, my Tongue unapt for talk;</l>
                  <l>And unaccuſtom'd to thoſe ſofter terms,</l>
                  <l>Which Charm that fair, that dear believing Sex.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Damp.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Let me but know what you would have me do,</l>
                  <l>And think it done: think your ſelf happy, Sir,</l>
                  <l>If in my power it be to make you ſo.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Beauf.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thou then ſhalt break the Ice, prepare the way.</l>
                  <l>Thou haſt a tongue, nimble and fluent</l>
                  <l>As the well feed Lawyers, ſoft and ſmooth</l>
                  <l>As the old crafty Courtiers, who denies</l>
                  <l>Your ſute, yet would perſwade you he is ſtill</l>
                  <l>Your friend. Speak, wilt thou do it?</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Damp.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Sir, I will.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Beauf.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>But art thou ſure thou wilt?</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Damp.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Moſt certain, Sir.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:199141:7"/>
               <speaker>Beauf.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Haſt thou conſider'd well?</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Damp.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Yes, I have.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Beauf.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Perhaps already thou forget'ſt</l>
                  <l>Who 'tis I love.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Damp.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>No, it is <hi>Elvira,</hi> is it not?</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Beauf.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>It is indeed <hi>Elvira,</hi> but then ſure</l>
                  <l>There ſhould be more of that Dear Name than one<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </l>
                  <l>Hah! What ſayſt thou?</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Damp.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Not that I know of, Sir,</l>
                  <l>'Tis <hi>Grammount</hi>'s Wif<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> I mean.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Beauf.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thou ſhould'ſt have ſaid</l>
                  <l>Thy Brothers, thy Brothers<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Wife, on whom</l>
                  <l>Thy Uncle, the unhappy <hi>Beanfort</hi> doats.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Damp.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>I ſhould indeed, nor did I wave that word,</l>
                  <l>For any ſuch great kindneſs it imports,</l>
                  <l>As might o'erthrow the reſolution</l>
                  <l>I have made to ſerve you, Sir: no, were ſhe mine,</l>
                  <l>This fair <hi>Elvira</hi> mine, as ſhe is now</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Grammont</hi>'s; I'd not retract one ſyllable<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </l>
                  <l>Of what I have ſaid, but freely ſacrifice<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </l>
                  <l>My Life, my Honour, all in ſhort, that's dear</l>
                  <l>To your repoſe.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Beauf.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Come, come to my Arms then,</l>
                  <l>Let me embrace and hug thee, <hi>Dampierre.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>By Heaven thou art—a moſt illuſtrious</l>
                  <l>Villain, a rank Pander. Oh <hi>Grammount</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>How de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ply would thy Brothers baſeneſs wound</l>
                  <l>Thy generous Soul, could'ſt thou but gueſs</l>
                  <l>His foul intent. But thou art good, ſo true</l>
                  <l>To Virtue and to Honour, thou can'ſt ne'er</l>
                  <l>Think on a crime ſo Black, as this baſe wretch</l>
                  <l>Dares act; this miſerable wretch, who at</l>
                  <l>One fatal blow, would ſtrike a Dagger</l>
                  <l>To his Brothers Heart, damn both himſelf and me<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </l>
                  <l>And plunge us all into a horrid gulf</l>
                  <l>Of everlaſting miſery.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Damp.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>If my too forward zeal be an offence,</l>
                  <l>Puniſh my giddy raſhneſs as you pleaſe:</l>
                  <l>Yet do it, Sir, ſomething a gentler way.</l>
                  <l>Charge me not with ſuch black and horrid crimes,</l>
                  <l>As Heaven knows my very Soul deteſts.</l>
                  <l>Or rathertake my hated Life, ſee here,</l>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:199141:7"/>
                  <l>My naked breaſt ready to meet the blow,</l>
                  <l>My Tongue prepar'd to bleſs the hand that ſtrikes.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Beauf.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>I ſcorn to ſtain my Sword with ſuch baſe blood,</l>
                  <l>Live, and repent thy raſhneſs if thou can'ſt,</l>
                  <l>If not, reſolve never to ſee my face agen.</l>
                  <stage>Ex. Beauf.</stage>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Damp.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Not ſee your face agen, but on the terms</l>
                  <l>Of penitence, my noble Uncle. Yes,</l>
                  <l>Yes, but I ſhall, or I am much deceived.</l>
                  <l>This qualm of Conſcience, is in him no more,</l>
                  <l>Than a meer aguiſh fit; the cold one gone,</l>
                  <l>A hot one then will certainly ſucceed.</l>
                  <l>O all you black and diſmal fiends of Hell,</l>
                  <l>Who take delight in miſchiefs baneful ſport,</l>
                  <l>Feed ſtill, and blow up his inceſtuous flame</l>
                  <l>To a reſiſtleſs highth; then from his paſſion,</l>
                  <l>Ill conceal'd, as from a flowing ſpring</l>
                  <l>Let daily doubts, fears, jealouſies, heart burnings</l>
                  <l>And eternal jarrs, ariſe within theſe walls:</l>
                  <l>Let <hi>Beaufort</hi> hate <hi>Grammount, Grammount Elvira,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And <hi>Elvira</hi> both, whilſt <hi>Dampierre</hi> hates 'em all,</l>
                  <l>And juſtly too.</l>
                  <l>I was the firſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> pretender to <hi>Elvira,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>But by the faithleſs <hi>Grammount</hi> under-min'd,</l>
                  <l>All my beſt hopes ſoon vaniſht into air,</l>
                  <l>And I beheld her circled in his Arms.</l>
                  <l>Nor durſt I then think of revenge on him</l>
                  <l>That did the wrong, he was but too ſecure,</l>
                  <l>Supported by a partial Uncle's power,</l>
                  <l>And by <hi>Elvira</hi>'s Friends. But now I know</l>
                  <l>That <hi>Beaufort</hi> doats on her, from this dear day</l>
                  <l>I date my hopes of a ſevere revenge.</l>
                  <l>But ſee, <hi>Grammount</hi> appears in cloſe diſcourſe</l>
                  <l>With his inſeparable friend <hi>Montigny:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>My mind at preſent's ſtrangely ruffled,</l>
                  <l>Therefore I'll withdraw, ere they perceive me.</l>
                  <stage>Ex. Damp.</stage>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Grammount <hi>and</hi> Montigny.</stage>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gram.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Bleſt in the ſofteſt Paſſion of my Soul,</l>
                  <l>Poſſeſſing, in my dear <hi>Elvira,</hi> all</l>
                  <l>The world calls Vertuous, or my eyes think fair;</l>
                  <l>How can I, friend, without a bluſh complain,</l>
                  <l>Or murmur midſt ſuch vaſt, ſuch charming joys,</l>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:199141:8"/>
                  <l>As taſted once, would make an Anchoret</l>
                  <l>Forget his way to Heaven, and think to find</l>
                  <l>It here below.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mont.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Forbear, my deareſt friend,</l>
                  <l>Take heed, ſhould'ſt thou be raſh enough to pine,</l>
                  <l>Whileſt with a liberal hand, kind Heaven</l>
                  <l>Pours all it's choiceſt bleſſings on thy Head,</l>
                  <l>Such black ingratitude, no doubt, would be</l>
                  <l>Severely puniſht by ſome ſignal judgment</l>
                  <l>From above.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gram.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Unkind, cruel <hi>Montigny,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Thou know'ſt, at each ſad thought of loſing thee,</l>
                  <l>Tho circled in my dear <hi>Elvira</hi>'s Arms,</l>
                  <l>I feel ſuch ſtrange diſtructing pangs of grief,</l>
                  <l>As nought but the moſt perfect friendſhip</l>
                  <l>Can excuſe; ſo vaſt, ſo ſenſible a pain,</l>
                  <l>As wounds my very Soul, and damps and ſoures</l>
                  <l>The ſweeteſt joys of a poſſeſſing Lover.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mont.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thou beſt of Men, and deareſt too of Friends,</l>
                  <l>Let me embrace, and hug, and preſs thee thus,</l>
                  <l>Near to that heart which owns no other bands,</l>
                  <l>But thoſe of everlaſting friendſhip for</l>
                  <l>The generous <hi>Grammount:</hi> Heaven knows with what</l>
                  <l>Regret I leave thee, Friend; yet muſt we part.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gram.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>O ſay not ſo, each word's a mortal wound,</l>
                  <l>Each ſyllable a Dagger to my heart.</l>
                  <l>Rather recall the haſty ſentence, and</l>
                  <l>Repenting thy unkindneſs, give me Life,</l>
                  <l>And what I value more, my Friend.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mont.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>O my <hi>Grammount,</hi> forbear; thy kindneſs elſe</l>
                  <l>Will be the ruin of thy friend; do not,</l>
                  <l>Oh do not force me to repeat,</l>
                  <l>What equally afflicts my Soul as thine,</l>
                  <l>It muſt be ſo.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gram.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>It muſt not, by all that's good,</l>
                  <l>Thou art no more tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Friend I took thee for,</l>
                  <l>If thou canſt thus forſake me, leave me thus,</l>
                  <l>And not give one poor ſhadow of a reaſon</l>
                  <l>For ſo ſevere a ſeparation.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mont.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Honor, my Friend, 'tis honour calls me hence:</l>
                  <l>Honour, that Idol to which all muſt bow.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:199141:8"/>
               <speaker>Gram.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Honour! whither can Honour call thee friend,</l>
                  <l>That <hi>Grammount</hi> would not go to ſhare the Prize?</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mont.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Whileſt I lie here, ſupinely ſurfeiting</l>
                  <l>On all the joys of ſoft bewitching eaſe;</l>
                  <l>My aged Sire, laden with years and fame,</l>
                  <l>Plays the young man, and makes the <hi>Spaniards</hi> feel</l>
                  <l>The ſmart of Wounds, I only ſhould have given.</l>
                  <l>Thither I go, thither I fly, my Friend,</l>
                  <l>To court fair Honour in the midſt of Blood,</l>
                  <l>Horror and dire Confuſion.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gram.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thoſe Frontier bickerings call not for thee,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Montigny,</hi> there's little honor to be gain'd:</l>
                  <l>But if thou art reſolv'd to go, refuſe not</l>
                  <l>Th' aſſiſtance of my Sword, oh let me ſhare</l>
                  <l>The Toyl, and Glory, with my deareſt Friend.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mont.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thou muſt no more think on the Wars, <hi>Grammount,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>But from the Genial bed, reaping the ſweet</l>
                  <l>Reward of all thy glorious labours paſt,</l>
                  <l>Raiſe up a race of Hero's, whoſe bright fame,</l>
                  <l>For early vertues, may ſoon equal thine.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gram.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Since honours ſtricteſt Laws muſt yield to Love,</l>
                  <l>Let Beauty then prevail, tho friendſhip cannot.</l>
                  <l>I have a Siſter, by the world thought fair,</l>
                  <l>Virtuous and young ſhe is: her Fortune's ſuch</l>
                  <l>As may at leaſt equal the largeſt hopes</l>
                  <l>Of the moſt Noble Youths our Age can ſhew:</l>
                  <l>If thou canſt learn to Love my Friend, ſhe's thine</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mont.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>How Prodigal! how Laviſh my <hi>Gram.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Thy Friendſhip makes thee, with a careleſs hand</l>
                  <l>Thou ſcatter'ſt Treaſures ſhou'd be the Reward</l>
                  <l>Of a vaſt merit only: or the price</l>
                  <l>Of many great and glorious Services.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gram.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Nay now thou trifleſt—</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mont.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>By Heaven I do not:</l>
                  <l>Tho yet my heart a ſtranger be to Love,</l>
                  <l>Yet 'tis with admiration I behold</l>
                  <l>The rare perfections of that beauteous Maid,</l>
                  <l>But I muſt ſtudy to deſerve her, friend.</l>
                  <l>Happy, if after all the nobleſt toiles</l>
                  <l>I may aſpire to ſuch a recompenc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</l>
                  <l>And with thy leave, my generous <hi>Grammount,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:199141:9"/>
                  <l>Lay all the Trophies of ſucceſsfull War</l>
                  <l>At the fair Charming <hi>Leonora</hi>'s Feet.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gram.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Away preach to rough Seamen in a Storm,</l>
                  <l>Or whiſper to the boiſterous Winds when in</l>
                  <l>Their lowdeſt fury, and they ſhall ſooner</l>
                  <l>Hearken to thy tale than I: But ſee,</l>
                  <l>My dear <hi>Elvira</hi> coming to my aid,</l>
                  <l>And <hi>Leonora</hi> too; thou canſt not ſure</l>
                  <l>Hope to maintain thy ground againſt us all.</l>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Elvira <hi>and</hi> Leonora.</stage>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Elv.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>From thoſe dark Clouds which in thy Face appear,</l>
                  <l>My boading heart foretells a riſing Storm</l>
                  <l>Of grief within thy Breaſt, ſpeak, my <hi>Grammount,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>what ruder cares, to thy <hi>Elvira</hi> yet</l>
                  <l>Unknown, ſit heavy on thy drooping Soul?</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gram.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thou beſt of Women, pard'n the guilty cauſe</l>
                  <l>Of this diſorder in my troubled mind.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Elv.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Oh name not pardon, but quickly let me ſhare,</l>
                  <l>And bear an equal part of all thy care.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gram.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Haſt thou not ſeen ſome men, extremely Rich,</l>
                  <l>Tell me <hi>Elvira,</hi> 'mongſt their deareſt ſtore</l>
                  <l>Of Gold, and Silver, Jewels, and other things</l>
                  <l>Of higheſt value, lock ſecurely up</l>
                  <l>Some pretty, favourite toy:</l>
                  <l>Who when returning to review their wealth,</l>
                  <l>And miſſing only that, yet could not bear</l>
                  <l>The petty loſs, tho all the reſt were ſafe?</l>
                  <l>The caſe, my dear <hi>Elvira,</hi> is my own,</l>
                  <l>Thou art the deareſt treaſure of my Soul,</l>
                  <l>Thou art—</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Elv.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Forbear, <hi>Grammount,</hi> I gueſs the reſt,</l>
                  <l>Tho not ſo much from what thou now haſt ſaid,</l>
                  <l>As from <hi>Montigny</hi>'s ſilence, and thy grief.</l>
                  <l>Each ſeems a like concern'd, each dreads the loſs</l>
                  <l>Of a dear friend; yet, you <hi>Montigny,</hi> will,</l>
                  <l>Nay muſt be gone.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gram.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Muſt, oh no, alaſs!</l>
                  <l>He will be gone, uncall'd, unask'd, unſent for,</l>
                  <l>He will forſake his friend. Oh <hi>Elvira,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Oh <hi>Leonora,</hi> yet try all you can,</l>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:199141:9"/>
                  <l>Your ſofteſt Arts, to move this cruel Man.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Elv.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>What may be done let us reſolve to do,</l>
                  <l>I for a Husband plead, a Brother you.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Sure friendſhips cauſe, argued before a friend,</l>
                  <l>Cannot but meet with a ſucceſsfull end.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mont.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Such powerful advocates who can withſtand?</l>
                  <l>Honour! thou ſtrange fantaſtick airy thing,</l>
                  <l>Thou loſing bargain to the braveſt Souls,</l>
                  <l>Thou eaſie purchaſe, coſtly to maintain,</l>
                  <l>Thou cloke to bold ambition's reſtleſs hopes;</l>
                  <l>No more, to thy capricious humours will</l>
                  <l>I blindly bow, nor court thee as a ſlave.</l>
                  <l>The preſent time to friendſhip I will give,</l>
                  <l>And what that ſpares, ſhall be intirely thine;</l>
                  <l>Still all that man in reaſon ought, I'll do</l>
                  <l>To ſatisfie my Friend and Honour too.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Elv.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>See my <hi>Grammount,</hi> the cruel man repents,</l>
                  <l>Friendſhip has wrought its much deſir'd effect,</l>
                  <l>And fixt the Rover here.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>What would you more?</l>
                  <l>He yields and gives you the glory of the day;</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mont.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Half vanquiſht by my friend, I durſt not<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſt and</l>
                  <l>The ſhock of ſo much Beauty as you brought</l>
                  <l>To Storm the Fort: Honour it ſelf durſt not</l>
                  <l>Pretend to hold it out againſt ſuch odds.</l>
                  <l>Can you, my Friend, pardon a proud Rebell</l>
                  <l>Now imploring Grace?</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gram.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Talk not of Pardon, my Friend,</l>
                  <l>Give me thy Hand, <hi>Elvira, Montigny</hi> thine.</l>
                  <l>Thus guarded, I dare challenge all the World,</l>
                  <l>To ſhow but one Man more, as happy, as</l>
                  <l>My ſelf. Methinks mankind ſhould envy me,</l>
                  <l>Thus bleſt in a laſting full fruition</l>
                  <l>Of all thoſe glorious Charms, the ſweeteſt love,</l>
                  <l>Or trueſt, deareſt friendſhip can afford.</l>
                  <l>Henceforth, be every day, within theſe Walls,</l>
                  <l>By all, kept as a ſolemn Feſtival,</l>
                  <l>Sacred to Love and Friendſhip: and to me,</l>
                  <l>May both, as now, ever propitious be.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <trailer>The End of the Firſt ACT.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="act">
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:199141:10"/>
            <head>ACT II. SCENE I.</head>
            <stage>
               <hi>Enter</hi> Dampierre <hi>pulling in</hi> Lyſette.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Damp</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>NAy prethee why ſo refractory?</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Lyſet.</hi> I am in haſte, or if I were not,</l>
                  <l>What buſineſs pray can you have with me?</l>
                  <l>You, who have ſcarce vouchſafed</l>
                  <l>One look this way, this long, long</l>
                  <l>Day or two.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Damp.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Buſineſs of importance Child,</l>
                  <l>And ſuch as in the end might prove</l>
                  <l>To thy advantage if diſcreetly manag'd.</l>
                  <l>But—</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lyſet.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>But what, nay pray out with it.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Damp.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Why, thou art a very fooliſh ignorant</l>
                  <l>Young Wench, that ever ſtand'ſt in thy</l>
                  <l>Own light.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lyſet.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Your wiſdom's much miſtaken in my</l>
                  <l>Character, I dare aſlure you Sir,</l>
                  <l>For I am n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ither ſo ſilly, nor ſo igonrant,</l>
                  <l>I thank my kinder Stars, but that I very</l>
                  <l>Well underſtand the poſt I am in, with all</l>
                  <l>The by-advantages, that may be made by</l>
                  <l>One of my profeſſion that has wit.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Damp.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Wit! prethee of what uſe is Wit in your</l>
                  <l>Commonwealth, hah!</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lyſet</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Oh, Sir, believe me, that Waiting-woman</l>
                  <l>That wants it, is the greateſt ſlave in</l>
                  <l>Nature. Whereas we that have it, rather</l>
                  <l>Command than ſerve, and in a very little</l>
                  <l>Time b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>come real Miſtreſſes, whilſt</l>
                  <l>They, poor Ladies, only enjoy the empty,</l>
                  <l>Uſeleſs Title.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Damp.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Good!</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:199141:10"/>
               <speaker>Lyſet.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>For by our witty, ſly, and ſubtle inſinuations,</l>
                  <l>We at length become ſo abſolutely neceſſary to 'em,</l>
                  <l>That they live not but in us;</l>
                  <l>They ſee with our Eyes, here with our ears,</l>
                  <l>And judge not of any thing but by our wiſe</l>
                  <l>Directions.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Damp.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Admirable!</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lyſet.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>So that if love once fires their tender Hearts,</l>
                  <l>'Tis we that either fan the growing flames,</l>
                  <l>Or elſe ſuppreſs them quite.</l>
                  <l>Wiſely, we manage their inclinations</l>
                  <l>To our beſt advantage: and ſuffer 'em to love,</l>
                  <l>But when, and where, as little, or as much,</l>
                  <l>As we think fit.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Damp.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Incomparable!</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lyſet.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>In ſhort, Sir,</l>
                  <l>It is by our all powerful intereſt,</l>
                  <l>That the ugly, and the awkwerd fool, if liberal,</l>
                  <l>Succeeds in his Amours: Whilſt the gay,</l>
                  <l>Well bred, handſom wit, too oft miſcarries</l>
                  <l>By his unſeaſonable thrift.</l>
                  <l>'Tis we indeed, do all, gain us, and they are yours;</l>
                  <l>Proportion but your gifts, to your deſires,</l>
                  <l>And you can never fail: Since to confeſs</l>
                  <l>The very truth, 'tis we that ſet to ſale,</l>
                  <l>Their favours, and good graces of all ſorts</l>
                  <l>And ſizes, even from a ſimple, ſingle ſmile,</l>
                  <l>To full fruition, Sir.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Damp</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Hold, hold, enough: the world cannot produce</l>
                  <l>Thy equal, here, here's Gold for thee.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lyſet.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>For me, Sir, and why, I pray?</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Damp.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>No matter Child, here's yet more take it,</l>
                  <l>And deſerve it, Girl.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lyſet.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Let me but know which way,</l>
                  <l>And much may be done.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Damp.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Why, watch <hi>Elvira</hi> narrowly, let not</l>
                  <l>One look, one ſmile eſcape thy diligence,</l>
                  <l>Never be from her, but be a conſtant Spy</l>
                  <l>On all her actions.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lyſet.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Ple do't:</l>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:199141:11"/>
                  <l>And yet, I doubt, I ſhall but loſe</l>
                  <l>My labour, and you your mony,</l>
                  <l>At leaſt, if you expect any thing</l>
                  <l>Extraordinary from my obſervations.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Damp.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>No matter, I'le venter my money.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Leyſt.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>And I my pains: tho I am confident</l>
                  <l>You will be ſtrangely diſappointed,</l>
                  <l>When from an exact Diary of all her</l>
                  <l>Actions, you will only find, that of</l>
                  <l>Sixteen long hours, ſhe dayly ſpends,</l>
                  <l>At leaſt twelve in Prayer, or fulſom</l>
                  <l>Dalliance with her onw lawful Husband.</l>
                  <l>And ſo I am your Humble Servant, Sir.</l>
                  <stage>Ex Lyſet.</stage>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Damp.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Go on, and proſper Girl:</l>
                  <l>For if I catch <hi>Elvira</hi> tripping,</l>
                  <l>Or can but find the leaſt appearance of a ſlip,</l>
                  <l>I'le quickly make a Mountain of a Molehill.</l>
                  <l>Then to <hi>Grammount</hi> I'le go, and tell him all,</l>
                  <l>Yet ſeem to leave much more behind untold:</l>
                  <l>So make him beg to know, what known ſhall pinch</l>
                  <l>And gall him to the quick. They love too well</l>
                  <l>For Man and Wife, and what's yet worſe,</l>
                  <l>So good an underſtanding between them,</l>
                  <l>Sutes not with mine, nor with my Uncles purpoſes.</l>
                  <l>But he retuns not, as I thought he would,</l>
                  <l>And to find out the reaſon, much perplexes me.</l>
                  <l>But ſee, where he comes, all melancholy,</l>
                  <l>Sad and penſive, almoſt loſt in his own</l>
                  <l>Wild diſtracting thoughts. The Devil now works</l>
                  <l>Hard, and I'le not be his hindrance: But wait,</l>
                  <l>Then take my time to lend a helping hand,</l>
                  <l>In this our common Buſineſs.</l>
                  <stage>He retires to a corner of the Stage.</stage>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Beaufort.</stage>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Beauf.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>How poor,</l>
                  <l>And how contempt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ble a thing is man,</l>
                  <l>Made but more wretched, by thoſe very ſame</l>
                  <l>Diſtinctive faculties of the Soul,</l>
                  <l>Which yet ſeem to ſooth, and flatter him,</l>
                  <l>With an imaginary Excellence,</l>
                  <l>Above the reſt of the Creation.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:199141:11"/>
               <speaker>Damp.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Good!</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Beauf.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Reaſon, what art thou, but the very ſource,</l>
                  <l>And ſpring, from whence flow all our miſeries?</l>
                  <l>Thou art that glimm'ring light, by which alone,</l>
                  <l>We can diſcern thoſe crimes, which otherwiſe,</l>
                  <l>We n'er had underſtood; at leaſt, as ſuch.</l>
                  <l>And ſo had known no guilt.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Damp.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Better and better!</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Beauf.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Our phlegmatick dull Prieſts, have all miſtook</l>
                  <l>Their errand ſure, and groſly hitherto</l>
                  <l>Impoſed upon the credulous world:</l>
                  <l>Whilſt with an erring Zeal, they've preach'd down Luſt,</l>
                  <l>Yet given a Paſs, to more pernicious Love.</l>
                  <l>For Luſt is, at the worſt, but a brisk,</l>
                  <l>Generous heat, and natural ferment</l>
                  <l>Of the blood, lay'd by the next dear Child</l>
                  <l>Of joy, that dares contribute to the cure.</l>
                  <l>But when the Devil tempts us to love one,</l>
                  <l>And only one: not all the Sex beſide,</l>
                  <l>Can quench the helliſh flame;</l>
                  <l>But be ſhe Mother, Daughter, Aunt, or Niece,</l>
                  <l>How near ſoever tyed to us by Blood,</l>
                  <l>It matters not: She, ſhe alone can cure,</l>
                  <l>That gave the fatal wound.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Damp<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>He's faſt enough, I am ſure, now I'le bolt.</l>
                  <l>If I dare venture to approach you, Sir,</l>
                  <l>It is with the ſame awful reverence,</l>
                  <l>As penitent ſinners do th' offended Gods:</l>
                  <l>With the ſame humble hopes too, that at length</l>
                  <l>Your mercy, o'r your juſtice, may prevail;</l>
                  <l>Pard'ning thoſe crimes I have with tears bewayl'd,</l>
                  <l>And would have expiated with my blood,</l>
                  <l>Would you have ſuffer'd it.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Beauf.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Ha! <hi>Dampierre,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And in this humble poſture too, nay then,</l>
                  <l>No change, to me, can ever appear ſtrange:</l>
                  <l>Since in ſo very, very, ſmall a time,</l>
                  <l>Thou art turn'd Saint, and I a Devil.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Damp.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Far be it, Sir, from me to aſſume</l>
                  <l>The Glorious title of a Saint, and yet,</l>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:199141:12"/>
                  <l>A very little time, may uſher in</l>
                  <l>Strange alterations. Believe mine real then,</l>
                  <l>And make your vertue, as remarkable</l>
                  <l>In pard'ning, as in cenſuring, a crime</l>
                  <l>Committed but in thought, and hatched there</l>
                  <l>Only by too warm a zeal, for the great</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Beauforts</hi> Service.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Beauf.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Curſe on thy ill tim'd change,</l>
                  <l>Which only comes, unſeaſonably now,</l>
                  <l>To upbraid my weakneſs.</l>
                  <l>Pard'n thee! Yes, withall my heart I pard'n thee,</l>
                  <l>But on this one condition let it be,</l>
                  <l>That thou n'er talk to m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> of vertue more.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Damp.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Alas, what mean you, Sir?</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Beauf.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Be wicked ſtill;</l>
                  <l>Be vitious, as thou ever wert,</l>
                  <l>Go boldly on, and ſtop at nothing.</l>
                  <l>Thy wanton fancy, repreſents as pleaſing</l>
                  <l>To thy ſenſes, but gratifie'em all,</l>
                  <l>Even to a loath'd ſatiety.</l>
                  <l>Then come, and waving all uneaſie qualms,</l>
                  <l>Teach by experience the vaſt pleaſure</l>
                  <l>Of unbounded vice: gladly I'le hear thee,</l>
                  <l>And become thy wanton Proſelyte, my great,</l>
                  <l>My glorious Maſter.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Damp.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Heaven protect you, Sir,</l>
                  <l>Now you talk ſtrangely; perhaps you doubt me,</l>
                  <l>And this way only hope to learn the truth:</l>
                  <l>For you, I know, are eminently good</l>
                  <l>And vertuous.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Beauf.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Hah! that lie will damm thee</l>
                  <l>Paſt all hopes of mercy: I am nor good,</l>
                  <l>Nor vertuous, but, by much, more wicked,</l>
                  <l>Than an honeſt heart dares think. I rage,</l>
                  <l>I burn in an Unlawful, and Inceſtuous flame:</l>
                  <l>Alas! there's a perpetual tumult</l>
                  <l>In my diſtracted mind, nor can I fix</l>
                  <l>One wandering thought, but what ſtill leads me</l>
                  <l>To the very brink of Hell. Oh <hi>Elvira</hi>—</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:199141:12"/>
               <speaker>Damp.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Forget her, Sir, I once dearly lov'd her,</l>
                  <l>Yet when I found ſhe could prefer,</l>
                  <l>My Brother's tardy paſſion before mine,</l>
                  <l>I quickly ſhook the lazy off, and</l>
                  <l>With an indiffernt eye, could ſafely gaze</l>
                  <l>On all thoſe Beauties I before adored.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Beauf.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Forget her! no, too eaſily alas!</l>
                  <l>I can forget that ſhe is <hi>Grammount</hi>'s Wife,</l>
                  <l>Or <hi>Beaufort</hi>'s Niece, but that ſhe is fair,</l>
                  <l>That ſhe is charming, above all others</l>
                  <l>Of her Beauteous Sex, that, that, I never</l>
                  <l>Can forget.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Damp.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>If you muſt think on her,</l>
                  <l>Think then, at the ſame time, on her too rigid</l>
                  <l>Vertue, that eternal bar to all your</l>
                  <l>Guilty hopes.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Beauf.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>There is no bar to impetuous Love,</l>
                  <l>At leaſt, Vertue I'am ſure is but a weak one.</l>
                  <l>But why do I vainly talk of Vertue?</l>
                  <l>I am convinced, there's no ſuch thing on Earth.</l>
                  <l>No, all's but pretence, all's meer Hypocriſie.</l>
                  <l>Look <hi>Dampierre,</hi> round this vaſt Machine the World,</l>
                  <l>'Tis but a larger Theater, on which</l>
                  <l>Each skilful Actor, plays that part alone,</l>
                  <l>Which, for his profit, he can manage beſt.</l>
                  <l>Come then unmask: thou ſeeſt my naked heart,</l>
                  <l>To all the world beſide, be the reformed,</l>
                  <l>The good, the pious <hi>Dampierre,</hi> but to me,</l>
                  <l>Be what thou ever wert.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Damp.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Hah! what's that, Sir?</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Beauf.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Nay perhaps I may not find a name for't,</l>
                  <l>That may pleaſe you: But to be plain, and ſhort,</l>
                  <l>Help me to the enjoyment of <hi>Elvira,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And I'll diſclaim <hi>Grammount,</hi> I'll cut off all</l>
                  <l>His fairer hopes, to make a way for thee,</l>
                  <l>My darling, to the poſſeſſion of my</l>
                  <l>Envied Wealth.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:199141:13"/>
               <speaker>Damp.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Miſled, by a too haſty Zeal,</l>
                  <l>I made an offer once, not all your wealth,</l>
                  <l>Nor even that of the whole world,</l>
                  <l>Can e're prevail with me to make again</l>
                  <l>That kindneſs then was ſlighted, ſcorn'd, repai'd</l>
                  <l>With cruel injuries, and a boiſterous</l>
                  <l>Storm of black reproaches.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Beauf.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Upbraid me not</l>
                  <l>With what is paſt.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Damp.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>By what is paſt, I but</l>
                  <l>Too plainly ſee, the kind return my beſt</l>
                  <l>Endeavours, for your ſervice, in that kind,</l>
                  <l>Are ſure to meet with.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Beauf.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>By various and inſulting Paſſions agitated,</l>
                  <l>I felt unheard of torments in my mind,</l>
                  <l>My very Soul was, as it were, ſtretched on</l>
                  <l>The Rack, and all that ſtorm, was nought but the</l>
                  <l>Strong Convulſions of a dying Vertue.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Damp.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Heaven forbid, the generous <hi>Beaufort</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>So much renowned for ſolid Vertue, ſhould</l>
                  <l>In a Storm of Paſſion, yet make ſhipwreck</l>
                  <l>Of it all: No, to the Wars, Sir, there—</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Beauf.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Talk not to me of War, too long already</l>
                  <l>I have toyl'd i'th' barren Fields of <hi>Mars,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Waſted my Youth and Vigor in rough Camps,</l>
                  <l>And bloody broils: Deaf to the Virgins Plaints,</l>
                  <l>The Widows Curſes, or the Orphans Cries,</l>
                  <l>For Lovers, Husbands, Parents, Butcher'd all</l>
                  <l>In hateful War. In ſhort, I loath that Trade</l>
                  <l>Of cutting throats, and am reſolv'd henceforth</l>
                  <l>To Love, and that <hi>Elvira</hi> too.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Damp.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Oh, Sir, think what the cenſorious world will ſay.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Beauf.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>E'en let the world ſay what it will:</l>
                  <l>I care not, ſhe, I'm ſure, is a meer</l>
                  <l>Stranger to my blood. Come then, be once more</l>
                  <l>Kind, I know thou lov'ſt me, <hi>Dampierre,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>I know thou do'ſt.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Dam.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>You may be well aſſured I do.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:199141:13"/>
               <speaker>Beauf.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>O let me embrace, and hold thee in theſe Arms,</l>
                  <l>Till thou haſt granted all I can deſire.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Damp.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Had you before been half thus kind?</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Beauf.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>It is not now too late.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Damp.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Fool that I am, to ſtand here, only to</l>
                  <l>Be tempted to my Ruin. Oh! why</l>
                  <l>Do I not rather fly, not from you only,</l>
                  <l>But, for your ſake, from all Mankind?</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Beauf.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Nay, now thou art too cruel: Come, thou muſt,</l>
                  <l>Thou ſhalt, thou wilt.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Damp.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Alas! What would you have me do?</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Beauf.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Go to <hi>Elvira.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Damp.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Well, for once I will.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Beauf.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Tell her—by Heav'n I know not what—tell her—</l>
                  <l>Yes—if ſhe delights in martial Stories,</l>
                  <l>Tell her the many glorious Deeds I've done</l>
                  <l>In War, the bloody Battles I have won,</l>
                  <l>The Towns I have taken: Tell her, in ſhort,</l>
                  <l>All that may make her hearken to the Name</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>Beaufort</hi> with Delight.</l>
                  <l>Then, in a gentle Sigh, tell her I die</l>
                  <l>For Love, and if, after all that, thou dareſt</l>
                  <l>Proceed yet further, tell her at laſt</l>
                  <l>It is for her I die.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Damp.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Something like this, I am reſolved to do,</l>
                  <l>But cannot yet tell what. I<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>ll inſtantly</l>
                  <l>Go to her, and with my utmoſt Cunning</l>
                  <l>Try to dive to the very bottom</l>
                  <l>Of her Heart: Where if I find yet any</l>
                  <l>Room for a new Paſſion, you may be well</l>
                  <l>Aſſured, that to your beſt Advantage,</l>
                  <l>I will turn the Weakneſs of her yielding Mind.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Beauf.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Go, fly: Oh may we both ſucceſsful prove,</l>
                  <l>Thou in thy ſubtle Arts, and I in love.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <trailer>The End of the Second Act.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="act">
            <head>ACT III. SCENE I. <hi>A Foreſt.</hi>
            </head>
            <stage>Leonora <hi>alone.</hi>
            </stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>WHilſt all rejoyce, <hi>Montigny,</hi> at thy ſtay, only waſte in Tears the time away:</l>
                  <l>Uncertain, what to hope, or what to fear,</l>
                  <l>I wiſh thee gone, yet fain would keep thee here.</l>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:199141:14"/>
                  <l>All <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ays I try, to chaſe thee from my mind,</l>
                  <l>All Arts I uſe, yet can no Comfort find:</l>
                  <l>For if, t'elude the Torments I endure,</l>
                  <l>My Hopes from Abſence ſeem t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> expect a Cure;</l>
                  <l>Even thoſe Hopes ridiculous appear,</l>
                  <l>Since how can he be abſent who's lodg'd here?</l>
                  <stage>Laying her Hand on her Heart.</stage>
                  <l>A welcom, yet a fatal Gueſt to me,</l>
                  <l>Whilſt I the Priſoner am, and he is free.</l>
                  <l>What then, poor <hi>Leonora,</hi> wilt thou do,</l>
                  <l>Thou loveſt alas! but art forbid to woo,</l>
                  <l>That is Man's dear prerogative alone,</l>
                  <l>Thou muſt in ſecret ſigh, in ſecret moan:</l>
                  <l>And taught by ſtricter Rules of Modeſty,</l>
                  <l>What moſt thou lov'ſt thou muſt pretend to flie.</l>
                  <l>Thus ſtrangely wretched, ſurely there can be,</l>
                  <l>For all thy Woes, but one ſad Remedy:</l>
                  <l>Die then, yet in thy Death, ſo lucky prove,</l>
                  <l>That all the World may know, thou diedſt for love.</l>
                  <l>Each Poet then, thy Paſſion will rehearſe,</l>
                  <l>Sing thy ſad Fate in everlaſting Verſe,</l>
                  <l>And every Lover ſtrew thy paſſing Herſe.</l>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Elvira <hi>and</hi> Lyſette.</stage>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lyf.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>See Madam, where ſhe is.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Elv.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Retire a little.</l>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Ex.</hi> Lyſette</stage>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Oh Heavens! I am ſurpriz'd.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Elv.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>What? in this diſmal ſolitary Place</l>
                  <l>Alone, and all in Tears, my Dear?</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thoſe treacherous Teras will be my Ruine.</l>
                  <stage>Aſide.</stage>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Elv.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Nay, ſeek not to hide 'em from your deareſt</l>
                  <l>Friend, that would be too unkind: Oh! rather,</l>
                  <l>Let me know the unhappy Cauſe of this</l>
                  <l>Diſorder.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>I will, but you ſhall paſs your Word then,</l>
                  <l>Not to laugh at me.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Elv.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>My deareſt Child, I do,</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Nay, but I am confident you will laugh,</l>
                  <l>Since I my ſelf indeed, can ſcarce forbear,</l>
                  <l>When I reflect on it.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Elv.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>I will not,</l>
                  <l>Nay, I cannot laugh at what moves thee to weep.</l>
                  <l>Thy Tears, my Dear, would extort Pity</l>
                  <l>From an Enemy, much more from one that loves thee.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>This your unmerited Kindneſs, Madam,</l>
                  <l>makes me yet more aſhamed than ever,</l>
                  <l>To betray my Folly<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> For it was nothing more,</l>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:199141:14"/>
                  <l>Believe me, than a meer childiſh Paſſion.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Elv.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Whate'er it was, imparting it to me,</l>
                  <l>You will oblige me much.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Were it a Secret,</l>
                  <l>Or of the leaſt Importance, I would ne'er</l>
                  <l>Try to conceal it from you: Be ſo kind,</l>
                  <l>Dear Madam, as to impute my Folly</l>
                  <l>To my tender Years.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Elv.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Ah <hi>Leonora!</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>'Tis not your Folly, but your Cunning now,</l>
                  <l>That I have reaſon to complain of.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Were I as capable of Cunning, Madam,</l>
                  <l>As you believe I am, yet certainly</l>
                  <l>I would not uſe it to impoſe on you,</l>
                  <l>To whom I ſtand ſo many ways engag'd.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Elv.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>I know you ought not, yet I'm ſure you do.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Suſpect it not, indeed you wrong me much.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Elv.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>No, 'tis you that wrong your ſelf, wrong me,</l>
                  <l>And all our mutual Vows of Friendſhip too.</l>
                  <l>For know, that with no ſmall concern of late,</l>
                  <l>I have obſerv<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>d your gayer Humour fade,</l>
                  <l>And change into a ſad, dull and deadly</l>
                  <l>Melancholy: With Grief I have beheld</l>
                  <l>You fly all ſorts of pleaſing Company,</l>
                  <l>Only to court Retirement in ſome Grove.</l>
                  <l>This made me ſet <hi>Lyſette</hi> to watch your Steps,</l>
                  <l>By whom, juſt now inform'd, That you were gone</l>
                  <l>This way alone, I quickly follow'd you,</l>
                  <l>Tho' not without ſome Apprehenſions,</l>
                  <l>From the diſmal Wildneſs of this uncouth place,</l>
                  <l>Altho' I knew <hi>Montigny</hi> and <hi>Grammount,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Were here before, ſeeking Diverſion<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </l>
                  <l>In theſe o'ergrown Woods. Come then confeſs,</l>
                  <l>What brought you to this unfrequented place?</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Ah, what would you have me do?</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Elv.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Tell me the Truth,</l>
                  <l>For ſhould you ſtill endeavour to conceal it,</l>
                  <l>The ſwelling Secret would, in time,</l>
                  <l>Grow too unruly for your tender Breaſt,</l>
                  <l>And force its way, at laſt, with much more Noiſe,</l>
                  <l>And eager Violence, than would be fit</l>
                  <l>For ſo much Innocence to own.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>I yield:</l>
                  <l>Your kind and tender importunity,</l>
                  <l>At length has con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uer'd all my Fears.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:199141:15"/>
                  <l>Share then that fatal ſecret which, of late,</l>
                  <l>Has robbed me of my Reſt, of all my Peace.</l>
                  <l>Yet ſpare, oh ſpare my Tongue, th'ungrateful Task,</l>
                  <l>Of naming what I ſtill muſt bluſh to own:</l>
                  <l>But let theſe Tears convey it to your Breaſt,</l>
                  <l>Whilſt on my tender Knees I thus implore</l>
                  <l>Your Pity, and your Pardon.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Elv.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Riſe, riſe, my Dear,</l>
                  <l>Take this Kiſs, and with it too my pardon,</l>
                  <l>My Pity, and my faithful promiſe,</l>
                  <l>To aſſiſt thee in thy Love: For Love it is,</l>
                  <l>If I muſt gueſs, that has poſſeſt thy Soul.</l>
                  <l>If ſo, my Dear, you muſt be plainer yet,</l>
                  <l>And name the happy object of your Vows</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Ah Madam, I doubt I have already</l>
                  <l>Said too much, for ſee, my Brother coming,</l>
                  <l>Oh give me Leave to hide my Grief from him,</l>
                  <l>And all the World but you.</l>
                  <stage>Enter <hi>Dampierre. Leonora</hi> runs out, and <hi>Elvira</hi> offering to follow her, is ſtaid by <hi>Dampierre.</hi>
                  </stage>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Damp.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Nay, Madam,</l>
                  <l>You muſt excuſe my Rudeneſs, I but ſeize</l>
                  <l>The next at Hand, to know by what ſtrange fate</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Dampierre</hi> of late is grown ſo terrible,</l>
                  <l>As to oblige you with ſuch eager haſte,</l>
                  <l>To fly him.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Elv.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>You cannot think your Siſter ſhould avoid you,</l>
                  <l>Nor ought you to believe I would.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Damp.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>But, Madam, may I not believe my Eyes?</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Elv.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>You may, for they can only tell you,</l>
                  <l>That <hi>Leonora</hi> fled, and that I followed,</l>
                  <l>And all perhaps without one Thought of you.</l>
                  <l>But you of late are ſtrangely alter'd ſure,</l>
                  <l>You would not elſe ſo eaſily ſuſpect</l>
                  <l>Your Friends of ſo much incivility;</l>
                  <l>Believe me 'tis a Fault ſcarce pard'nable.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Damp.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Since my too light Suſpicion ſeems a Crime,</l>
                  <l>With all Submiſſion I intreat your Pardon:</l>
                  <l>Alas! I am no more the Man I was—</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Elv.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Why, what ſtrange Misfortune has befallen you?</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Damp.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>So great a one i'th' perſon of my Friend,</l>
                  <l>As Heaven, in all its Anger, ſcarcely could.</l>
                  <l>Have ſent a greater. Ah! had thoſe fair Eyes,</l>
                  <l>Madam, beheld what theſe have lately ſeen,</l>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:199141:15"/>
                  <l>How much would they have loſt, by this time</l>
                  <l>Of their wonted luſtre: at leaſt, if ſorrow,</l>
                  <l>Sighs, or frequent tears, could have diminiſht it.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Elv.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>You think me very tender hearted ſure,</l>
                  <l>Or elſe have ſome ſtrange ſtory to relate,</l>
                  <l>Extremely moving.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Damp.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Believe me, Madam,</l>
                  <l>It is a tale would move the hardeſt heart</l>
                  <l>To ſome compaſſion: Think then, you ſee</l>
                  <l>A man, compleatly bleſt above all others,</l>
                  <l>In the richeſt gifts of Nature, and of</l>
                  <l>Fortune; a Man, renown'd abroad for Arms,</l>
                  <l>And no leſs famed at home for goodneſs,</l>
                  <l>And for Virtue.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Elv.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>You have ſaid enough,</l>
                  <l>To let me know he is your Friend, who e're he be:</l>
                  <l>But ſure a Man of his high Character,</l>
                  <l>Can never prove unfortunate enough</l>
                  <l>To want our Pity.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Damp.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Yet, Heaven knows, much more</l>
                  <l>Unfortunate he is, than either good,</l>
                  <l>Or great: In ſhort, he Loves, Loves where he ſcarce</l>
                  <l>Dares ever hope to be belov'd again;</l>
                  <l>So, ſadly lingers out a hated Life,</l>
                  <l>In all the torments of a deep deſpair.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Elv.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Believe me, 'tis pity he ſhould ſo miſplace,</l>
                  <l>His love on one, who ſure deſerves it not.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Damp.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>I'll not pretend to rate her mighty worth,</l>
                  <l>But only tell you ſhe is wondrous fair,</l>
                  <l>Fair as the faireſt of her charming Sex;</l>
                  <l>Fair as <hi>Elvira,</hi> as hard hearted too;</l>
                  <l>And what's yet worſt of all, like her, ſhe is</l>
                  <l>Married to another.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Elv.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>How! his paſſion</l>
                  <l>Then is criminal, and ſhould be hopeleſs.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Damp.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>'Tis criminal indeed, and yet the crime,</l>
                  <l>Renders it but the more conſpicuous;</l>
                  <l>Or if you will give me leave to ſay ſo,</l>
                  <l>Meritorious; dear Devil tempt me not.</l>
                  <stage>Aſide.</stage>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Elv.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>I underſtand you not, or if I did,</l>
                  <l>I am not now at leiſure to diſpute</l>
                  <l>The merits of a guilty paſſion:</l>
                  <l>But come, let us move homewards pray,</l>
                  <l>And leave the reſt to a more fitting time.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Damp.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>No time more fitting; nor no place more free</l>
                  <l>Than this.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:199141:16"/>
               <speaker>Elv.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>But I am weary, and want reſt.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Damp</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Here you may have it, if you pleaſe,</l>
                  <l>I beg you would hear me.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Elv.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>I cannot now.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Damp.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Say rather that you will not.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Elv.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>That would be rude.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Damp.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>And therefore only will not hear, becauſe</l>
                  <l>It is th' unlucky <hi>Dampierre</hi> that entreats.</l>
                  <l>Juſt Gods! muſt I be ſtill neglected,</l>
                  <l>Still deſpiſed, and whether for my ſelf I plead,</l>
                  <l>Or for another, ſtill cut ſhort? no, ſtay,</l>
                  <l>And tho you'll hear no more of his ſad tale,</l>
                  <l>Be pleas'd at leaſt to lend an ear to mine.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Elv.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>What mean you, <hi>Dampierre?</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Damp.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Since my friends paſſion is condemn'd, oh! give</l>
                  <l>Me Leave to entertain you with another;</l>
                  <l>Which tho not wholly innocent, perhaps,</l>
                  <l>Yet owing all it has of guilt in it,</l>
                  <l>To you alone, by you at leaſt, ſhould be</l>
                  <l>Eſteem'd as ſo.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Elv.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>You grow myſterious now,</l>
                  <l>Your looks are wild, and you much diſcompos'd.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Damp.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Behold me well: And in theſe troubled looks</l>
                  <l>Read the diſorder of my Soul; ſpringing</l>
                  <l>From Love, oppoſed by hatred and more ſweet</l>
                  <l>Revenge. Do you not tremble, Madam?</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Elv.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Why ſhould I tremble?</l>
                  <l>If Heaven, as I believe, protects</l>
                  <l>The Innocent, I am ſecure enough.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Damp.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>You are indeed, for love at length has got</l>
                  <l>The day; that little God, tho diſpoſſeſt</l>
                  <l>Some time by my too juſt reſentment,</l>
                  <l>Is now return'd Victorious to his Throne,</l>
                  <l>And firmly reinſtated in the Empire</l>
                  <l>Of my heart.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Elv.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>I do begin to underſtand you now:</l>
                  <l>But <hi>Dampierre,</hi> have a care, deſiſt in time,</l>
                  <l>All yet is well: but if you dare proceed,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Grammount</hi> ſhall ſurely know your good deſign.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Damp.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Tuſh:</l>
                  <l>Meer bugbear words to ſcare young ſinners with;</l>
                  <l>You would fain make me angry,</l>
                  <l>But I at preſent want the leiſure:</l>
                  <l>A ſofer, nobler paſſion rules my Soul.</l>
                  <l>I am all Love, all Fire, my wanton blood</l>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:199141:16"/>
                  <l>Runs high, ready to force a paſſage</l>
                  <l>Through my diſtended veins.</l>
                  <l>This gloomy place, invites us too to Love,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe kinder ſhades, not only will conceal</l>
                  <l>Our amorous Thefts, but even forbidding</l>
                  <l>Entrance to the Sun,</l>
                  <l>Will ſhroud us in an artificial night:</l>
                  <l>That all things may be done with greater decency.</l>
                  <l>Come then,</l>
                  <stage>Offers to kiſs her hand.</stage>
                  <l>Take this warm earneſt of a greater Bliſs,</l>
                  <l>And think, with how much pleaſure to your ſelf,</l>
                  <l>You may in one poor fleeting minutes time,</l>
                  <l>Even o'erpay me for an age of ſufferings.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Elv.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Monſter of a Man, Villain unhand me,</l>
                  <l>Let me quickly go, or I will fill theſe Woods</l>
                  <l>With cries, ſuch moving cries, as ſhall awake,</l>
                  <l>And from their diſmal hollow caverns draw,</l>
                  <l>Each nobler Beaſt of prey to be a Guard</l>
                  <l>To me, to thee baſe wretch, a ſhame and terrour.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Damp.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Come, come you need not uſe theſe common arts,</l>
                  <l>Theſe faint denials, little ſtrugling fits</l>
                  <l>May ſerve indeed as whets, to a weak</l>
                  <l>And puleing appetite: But mine is ſharp, wound</l>
                  <l>To the utmoſt pitch, keen as the greedy Hawks,</l>
                  <l>That's ready juſt to ſeize his long'd for prey.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Elv.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Lyſette, Lyſette:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Raſh, heedleſs Girl, oh whither art thou fled?</l>
                  <l>And thou, my dear <hi>Grammount,</hi> where art thou</l>
                  <l>Now? the diſtreſs'd <hi>Elvira</hi> wants thy help.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Damp.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Call louder yet, he anſwers not, perhaps</l>
                  <l>He may not now ſo much as think of you:</l>
                  <l>At leaſt you ſee he is not here to help you,</l>
                  <l>Therefore be wiſe, and what you cannot</l>
                  <l>Hope to avoid, ſubmit to patiently.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Elv.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Villain thou lieſt, he's in theſe very Woods.</l>
                  <l>Tremble, baſe wretch, at the bare thoughts</l>
                  <l>Of his approach; for tho he be not yet</l>
                  <l>Within the reach of my too feeble voice,</l>
                  <l>I doubt not but juſt Heaven will ſend him,</l>
                  <l>Either to reſcue, or revenge his dear <hi>Elvira:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And either way, to thy Confuſion Monſter.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Damp.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Hah! ſay you ſo, what muſt be done then,</l>
                  <l>Muſt be quickly done: and when 'tis done,</l>
                  <l>I'll truſt thee for betraying thy own ſhame</l>
                  <l>Scarce forty paces hence, there is a gloomy</l>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:199141:17"/>
                  <l>Place ſo private, as if kind nature had</l>
                  <l>Contrived it only for our uſe: There at</l>
                  <l>Thy beauteous ſhrine, I ll offer up my beſt</l>
                  <l>Devotions; and fill thee with ſuch melting</l>
                  <l>Joys, as firſt ſhall tempt thee to forgive,</l>
                  <l>Then make thee beg me to renew the Offence.</l>
                  <l>Nay hang not back, for if you do, by Heaven</l>
                  <l>I'll drag you thither.</l>
                  <stage>Offers to force her.</stage>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Elv.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Oh all you juſter</l>
                  <l>Powers above, ſend ſome relief: or give me</l>
                  <l>Strength enough to puniſh the baſe Villain.</l>
                  <l>Help, help, for Heaven's ſake help.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Damp.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Hah! what envious Devil has ſent him?</l>
                  <l>Oh, Madam, dry up thoſe precious Tears,</l>
                  <l>Forbear thoſe Cries, whilſt <hi>Dampierre</hi> lives</l>
                  <l>You're ſafe enough.</l>
                  <stage>He diſco<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ers <hi>Montigny</hi> at a diſtance.</stage>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Montigny.</stage>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mont.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Whence came thoſe diſmal Cries?</l>
                  <l>Hah; was it you, Madam, that ſo loudly</l>
                  <l>Call'd for help, ſpeak, Madam, ſpeak I beg you,</l>
                  <l>What means this ſtrange diſorder in your looks,</l>
                  <l>Or do thou <hi>Dampierre,</hi> I conjure thee, tell me</l>
                  <l>What was the matter?</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Damp.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>I know not I,</l>
                  <l>She ſurely beſt can tell what caus'd her fear:</l>
                  <l>Fortune, and her loud cries, directed me,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Montigny,</hi> as they have brought you hither.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Elv.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Generous <hi>Montigny,</hi> waſte not the time</l>
                  <l>In fruitleſs queſtions, but rather</l>
                  <l>If you have any friendſhip for <hi>Grammount,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Help, O quickly help me hence,</l>
                  <l>Whilſt I have yet ſome little ſtrength</l>
                  <l>Remaining.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Damp.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>If <hi>Dampierre,</hi> Madam,</l>
                  <l>May in any thing be ſerviceable,</l>
                  <l>Pray be ſo free as to command him too.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Elv.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Monſter, avoid my ſight.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Damp.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Hear you that, <hi>Montigny,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Look to her well, for much I fear ſhe's craz'd.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Elv.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Oh horrid impudence! but come, let us,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Montigny,</hi> fly this fatal place:</l>
                  <l>And yet my trembling joynts anſwer my haſte</l>
                  <l>But ill.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mont.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Fear nothing, Madam, but accept this hard</l>
                  <l>For your ſupport.</l>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Ex.</hi> Mont. <hi>and</hi> Elv.</stage>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:199141:17"/>
               <speaker>Damp.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Impudence aſſiſt me now,</l>
                  <l>Or elſe this one reverſe of Fortune</l>
                  <l>Ruins all, renders abortive all the</l>
                  <l>Hopeful projects of my labouring brain,</l>
                  <l>And leaves me naked to the mercy</l>
                  <l>Of offended juſtice. Curſe on my rebellious Blood,</l>
                  <l>Curſe on that flatt'ring opportunity,</l>
                  <l>Which ſmiled on, yet betray'd, my deareſt hopes.</l>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Grammount.</stage>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gram.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Well met Brother, ſaw you <hi>Montigny?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>I loſt him ſtrangely.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Dam.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Yes, juſt now I ſaw him.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gram.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Where, which way is he gone?</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Dam.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Homewards I think,</l>
                  <l>But make not too much haſte to overtake</l>
                  <l>Him, leaſt you ſhould chance to come</l>
                  <l>Before you are welcome.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gram.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>What mean you, <hi>Dampierre?</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Damp.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>I mean, that he's already in good Company,</l>
                  <l>And would not willingly admit of more.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gram.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>I fear it not, my friend to me is ever</l>
                  <l>Welcome, and by my ſelf I judge of him.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Damp.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>You may, and yet may be miſtaken too:</l>
                  <l>There are ſome certain times and ſeaſons,</l>
                  <l>When even the very beſt of friends</l>
                  <l>Are but importunate.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gram.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>That very minute,</l>
                  <l>My friend ſhould think me ſo, I ſhould think him</l>
                  <l>No more my friend.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Damp.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Be not too poſitive:</l>
                  <l>Suppoſe an aſſignation made by thee</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Grammount,</hi> to meet ſome kind, ſome yielding fair,</l>
                  <l>Here in this very favourable place;</l>
                  <l>And when that you were ready juſt to reap,</l>
                  <l>The deareſt fruits of many waking nights,</l>
                  <l>And painfull days, your friend ſhould then, juſt then</l>
                  <l>Rudely ruſh in to interrupt your joys.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gram.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>You are wanton, <hi>Dampierre,</hi> but at preſent</l>
                  <l>That's not <hi>Montigny</hi>'s caſe I'm ſure.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Damp.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>I hope it is not, yet I'll not ſwear</l>
                  <l>For any one.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gram.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Why, hope it is not?</l>
                  <l>Pray tell me, what from <hi>Montigny</hi>'s Conduct,</l>
                  <l>Can you, <hi>Dampierre,</hi> have, either to hope,</l>
                  <l>Or fear?</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:199141:18"/>
               <speaker>Damp.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Oh much, too much indeed,</l>
                  <l>Or elſe theſe eyes are ſhamefully miſtaken.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gram.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>This is all riddle, prithee be plainer.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Damp.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>You will allow, <hi>Grammount,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>That when two equal Gameſters meet to play</l>
                  <l>Upon the ſquare, each with a high opinion</l>
                  <l>Of the others honour, if in that caſe,</l>
                  <l>The one play foul, the other is thereby</l>
                  <l>Expoſed to a more certain loſs,</l>
                  <l>Than if he playd with one he knew to be</l>
                  <l>The moſt notorious Cheat alive?</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gram.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>No doubt o'nt, his confidence in th' others</l>
                  <l>Honour, makes him careleſs, blind to all</l>
                  <l>Thoſe little tricks, which in another,</l>
                  <l>He would ſoon diſcover.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Damp.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Well then, there's none ſo likely to diſcern the fraud;</l>
                  <l>As ſome good skillful honeſt ſtander by<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gram.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>'Tis granted.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Damp.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>I am that honeſt ſtander by,</l>
                  <l>Who in a ſtrange unequal game, ſee thee,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Grammount,</hi> moſt miſerably cheated:</l>
                  <l>Y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>re, I am your Brother, which ought</l>
                  <l>At leaſt to add ſome weight to what I ſay.</l>
                  <l>Take my advice then, e're it be too late,</l>
                  <l>And of a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l men beware <hi>Montigny,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>By whom you are betray'd, wrong'd, and abus'd,</l>
                  <l>Beyond all patience.</l>
                  <l>In ſhort, all in this world you hold moſt dear,</l>
                  <l>Eyes now at ſtake, whilſt he, that treacherous friend,</l>
                  <l>Plays foul, ſhamefully foul, thinking at one</l>
                  <l>Well managed throw, to rob you of your reſt,</l>
                  <l>Your honour, fixing an everlaſting ſtain</l>
                  <l>On you, and all your injur'd family;</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gram.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>My honour, <hi>Dampierre? Montigny</hi> ſeek to</l>
                  <l>Rob me of my Honour? Have a care,</l>
                  <l>And it thou lov<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>ſt thy ſelf-proceed no farther.</l>
                  <l>By heaven, thou art not ſafe, unleſs thou canſt</l>
                  <l>So plainly prove each guilty circumſtance</l>
                  <l>Againſt him, as can leave no room for doubt.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Damp.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Having diſcharg'd my duty I have done<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </l>
                  <l>If you are careleſs, well may I be ſo:</l>
                  <l>For tho I firmly do believe you wrong<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>d,</l>
                  <l>Yet is it not impoſſible for me</l>
                  <l>To be miſtaken, ſince chance perhaps,</l>
                  <l>Not aſſignation, may have brought them hither.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:199141:18"/>
               <speaker>Gram.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Curſe on thy double Tongue, hold me not thus</l>
                  <l>In doubt: but tell me quickly, what chance,</l>
                  <l>What aſſignation do'ſt thou dream of, Hah!</l>
                  <l>Tell me, who were they thou ſaw'ſt here?</l>
                  <l>Speak, wretch, ſpeak, or by all that's ſacred</l>
                  <l>I ſhall forget thou art my Brother.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Damp.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>You are ſtrangely paſſionate, tho all at laſt</l>
                  <l>May come to nothing: I only ſay</l>
                  <l>I ſaw 'em here, I mean <hi>Montigny</hi> and <hi>Elvira,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Here in this diſmal ſolitary place,</l>
                  <l>Alone too, but what of that, all places</l>
                  <l>Are alike, company, or no company,</l>
                  <l>'Tis all one, you now, to perſons that</l>
                  <l>Are vertuouſly inclined. And if you can</l>
                  <l>Believe them ſuch, why, there's an end of all.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gram.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Juſt Gods! that I ſhould ever live to hear,</l>
                  <l>The ſofteſt, tendereſt Wife, and trueſt friend</l>
                  <l>Thus to my face abuſed, yet muſt not puniſh</l>
                  <l>The offender.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Damp.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>You wrong your ſelf, <hi>Grammount,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>In raſhly blaming me, who jealous of</l>
                  <l>Your Honour, do in pure kindneſs only,</l>
                  <l>Speak my reaſonable fears.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gram.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>True:</l>
                  <l>I wrong my ſelf, my Wife, my Friend, and thee,</l>
                  <l>In blaming thee good, honeſt <hi>Dampierre:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Indeed I am aſhamed, that by too prompt</l>
                  <l>A paſſion, I ſhould ſeem to give thee ſo</l>
                  <l>Much credit, as ſhould make me entertain</l>
                  <l>The leaſt ſuſpicion, either of <hi>Elvira</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Or <hi>Montigny.</hi> Farewell unworthy man,</l>
                  <l>Be not hereafter ſo extremely jealous</l>
                  <l>Of my honour, but conſult your own.</l>
                  <l>And know, I wear a Sword, will do me right</l>
                  <l>Againſt all the world except a Brother.</l>
                  <stage>Ex. Gram.</stage>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Damp.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>So, now 'tis all againſt <hi>Dampierre,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Dampierre</hi> againſt all: no matter,</l>
                  <l>Thanks be to Fortune, and my lucky brain,</l>
                  <l>All things do yet go reaſonably well.</l>
                  <l>I have, by way of accuſation,</l>
                  <l>Got the ſtart both of <hi>Montigny</hi> and <hi>Elvira,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And that's no ſmall advantage, in my caſe.</l>
                  <l>For now whether <hi>Grammount</hi> begins with them,</l>
                  <l>Or they to him complain; in all appearance,</l>
                  <l>I am equally ſecure, ſince either way,</l>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:199141:19"/>
                  <l>Whate're is ſaid of me, will ſeem contriv'd</l>
                  <l>Only to blaſt my reputation,</l>
                  <l>And ſo be all ſuſpected: Wondrous good<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </l>
                  <l>Go bravely on then, <hi>Dampierre,</hi> puſh at all,</l>
                  <l>Honour attends th' attempt, tho thou ſhouldſt fall.</l>
                  <trailer>The end of the Third ACT.</trailer>
               </lg>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="act">
            <head>ACT IV. SCENE I.</head>
            <stage>
               <hi>Enter</hi> Elvira <hi>and</hi> Leonora.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>'TIs true, my Dear, your inconſiderate</l>
                  <l>And haſty flight, was tho the innocent,</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> the only cauſe of that adventu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e.</l>
                  <l>Alas! I tremble when I reflect</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> great danger you were in, and bluſh</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> I conſider I muſt call him Brother,</l>
                  <l>Who could be guilty of ſo barbarous</l>
                  <l>An attempt.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Elv.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>No more of that, for if you</l>
                  <l>Call him Brother, ſo does my dear <hi>Grammount,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>From whom with care this ſecret muſt be kept,</l>
                  <l>Leaſt a too juſt reſentment ſhould tranſport,</l>
                  <l>And hurry him beyond the limits of</l>
                  <l>His uſual moderation, ſo engage</l>
                  <l>The family in ſad and endleſs broils.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Your goodneſs, Madam, is beyond example,</l>
                  <l>But may there not be danger in it?</l>
                  <l>Some men are of ſo baſe a temper,</l>
                  <l>That a pard'n, proves but a new inducement</l>
                  <l>To 'em, to offend again.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Elv.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>'Tis in my power</l>
                  <l>To hinder his offending in that kind.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>'Tis true, and yet I cannot chooſe but fear,</l>
                  <l>Tho what, or why, I muſt confeſs I know not.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Elv</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Prethee no more of thy kind fears,</l>
                  <l>I apprehend not any thing, my dear,</l>
                  <l>Nor can I at the preſent think of ought</l>
                  <l>But of thy Paſſion, Child, 'tis a noble one,</l>
                  <l>Diſcreetly placed grounded on rational hopes.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:199141:19"/>
               <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>For Heavens ſake, Madam—</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Elv.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Nay, do not bluſh:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Montigny</hi>'s one of ſuch undoubted worth,</l>
                  <l>As juſtly may—but ſee where he comes,</l>
                  <l>Where is <hi>Grammount?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Montigny.</stage>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mont.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Gone, Madam, to the Governours Apartment,</l>
                  <l>Where he continues very buſie in</l>
                  <l>Diſpatching ſome affairs of great Concern.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Elv.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>It has been ſtill his chiefeſt care to eaſe</l>
                  <l>The Governour in all he could, and I</l>
                  <l>Am glad he ſtudies to oblige ſo good</l>
                  <l>And generous a Kinſman.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mont.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>His merit juſtly, Madam, claims that ſervice.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Elv.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>And my <hi>Grammount</hi> pays it moſt willingly.</l>
                  <l>Would he were here.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mont.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>I, Madam, wiſh it too,</l>
                  <l>Yet ſomething within me, what I know not,</l>
                  <l>Checks the fond wiſh, and makes me almoſt dread</l>
                  <l>Th' encounter of my deareſt friend. Alas!</l>
                  <l>How can I ever look him in the Face</l>
                  <l>Again, or hear him call me by the name</l>
                  <l>Of friend, whilſt <hi>Dampierre</hi> lives.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Elv.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Can you believe you ſhould oblige <hi>Grammount,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>In ſpilling of his only Brothers Blood.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mont.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>In puniſhing ſo exquiſite a Villain,</l>
                  <l>I do moſt certainly believe I ſhould.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Yet that Villain ſtill, is <hi>Grammount</hi>'s Brother;</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mont.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Brother, alas! what ſignifies the name</l>
                  <l>Or empty title of a Brother?</l>
                  <l>He who by vertue, or by kindneſs merits</l>
                  <l>The name of friend, is not a friend alone,</l>
                  <l>But even a Brother too, and much more ſo,</l>
                  <l>Than is the wretch that only claims by blood.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Elv.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Too low methinks, <hi>Montigny,</hi> you depreſs</l>
                  <l>Thoſe ſacred ties of blood, on which the world</l>
                  <l>Seems to rely ſo much.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Brother's a name</l>
                  <l>So dear, that the meer title only ſeems</l>
                  <l>Enough to juſtifie our kindneſs</l>
                  <l>For the very worſt of men.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mont.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>'Tis true,</l>
                  <l>Much is by cuſtom given to the name</l>
                  <l>Of Brother, and therefore only, 'tis,</l>
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:199141:20"/>
                  <l>Since decency diſarms my Friend</l>
                  <l>And will not ſuffer him to uſe his Sword,</l>
                  <l>That I believe my ſelf engaged in honour</l>
                  <l>To draw mine.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Elv.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Equally impious</l>
                  <l>In <hi>Grammount</hi> 'twould be to wiſh revenge,</l>
                  <l>As act it.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>And what he cannot wiſh without</l>
                  <l>A crime, you cannot do without a greater.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Elv.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>No more of this, I know <hi>Montigny</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>You are my <hi>Grammount</hi>'s deareſt Friend,</l>
                  <l>Conſult not then his Honour only,</l>
                  <l>But his repoſe, and that of all his Family.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mont.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Believe me, Madam, that's my only aim.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Elv.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>I do; and therefore beg you to conceal</l>
                  <l>This ſhameful ſtory. Oh bury it</l>
                  <l>In eternal ſilence, let not <hi>Beaufort,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Let not <hi>Grammount,</hi> ſuſpect the leaſt of <hi>Dampierre</hi>'s</l>
                  <l>Villany: but above all, beware of</l>
                  <l>Making it more publick by a quarrel.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mont.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Ah, Madam—</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Elv.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>I muſt not be denied, unleſs you have</l>
                  <l>A mind to ruin him you call your friend,</l>
                  <l>And ever robb him of his ſweeteſt reſt.</l>
                  <l>I do conjure you then by all your Vows</l>
                  <l>Of friendſhip to my dear <hi>Grammount,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>By all that's deareſt to you in this World—</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Elv.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Preſs it no further, Madam I Obey,</l>
                  <l>Tho Heaven knows I do it with regret.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Elv.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>We'll leave you to your cooler thoughts, <hi>Montigny,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Commending moderation ſtill, as beſt,</l>
                  <l>In this and all other caſes between friends.</l>
                  <l>Come <hi>Leonora.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Ex.</hi> Elv. Leon.</stage>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mont.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Juſt Heaven! how much</l>
                  <l>Beauty, how much goodneſs have you beſtow'd</l>
                  <l>On this one Woman.</l>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Ex.</hi> Montigny.</stage>
                  <stage>Enter <hi>Lyſette</hi> follow'd by <hi>Dampierre.</hi>
                  </stage>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Dam.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>What! threaten to turn thee out of Doors,</l>
                  <l>Baſely expoſe thee to the ſcorn</l>
                  <l>Of all thy laughing tribe, rail at,</l>
                  <l>And revile thee for a matter of juſt nothing?</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lyſet.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Nay, 'tis a fault not to be pardon'd,</l>
                  <l>And therefore I'm reſolved to be revenged.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Damp.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Fault! that's a name too ſoft, too mild,</l>
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:199141:20"/>
                  <l>For ſuch a crime: Why, 'tis Treaſon,</l>
                  <l>Downright Treaſon, a flat Conſpiracy</l>
                  <l>Againſt thy Empire Child.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lyſet.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Right, therefore once more I do pronounce</l>
                  <l>She ſinks under the mighty weight</l>
                  <l>Of my diſpleaſure.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Damp.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thou haſt it in thy power, my Girl,</l>
                  <l>To cruſh her into nothing.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lyſet.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>I have indeed, thanks to the dear delight</l>
                  <l>You take in miſchief, Sir.</l>
                  <l>But hark ye now, in cooler blood,</l>
                  <l>Pray tell me what mad pranks</l>
                  <l>You play'd i th' Foreſt, to put</l>
                  <l>My Saint-like Lady into ſuch Deviliſh Paſſion.</l>
                  <l>For when all<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>s done, my being out</l>
                  <l>Of the way ſo ſmall a time, was but an</l>
                  <l>Inconſiderable fault, too ſlight</l>
                  <l>To draw on ſo much anger.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Damp.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>No Pranks at all my Child,</l>
                  <l>Only an Argument aroſe by chance,</l>
                  <l>And I unluckily<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> maintained my part</l>
                  <l>With ſomething too much heat,</l>
                  <l>Which put her Ladyſhip into a horrid pelt,</l>
                  <l>And made her rail at me, at thee,</l>
                  <l>And every body elſe I think.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lyſet.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Yet, out of her abundant kindneſs,</l>
                  <l>She has forgiven me forſooth,</l>
                  <l>And once again received me into favour.</l>
                  <l>But that's no matter, I have not yet</l>
                  <l>Forgiven her: Nor will I, till to her coſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </l>
                  <l>I have made her know me better.</l>
                  <l>What! Pretend to turn me out of Doors,</l>
                  <l>No, my blood riſes at the very thoughts on't,</l>
                  <l>Say when ſhall I be Revenged?</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Damp.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>This night, this very hopeful night,</l>
                  <l>Nay if you let ſlip this night,</l>
                  <l>You may perhaps look long enuff</l>
                  <l>For ſuch another opportunity.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lyſet.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>With all my heart then, let it be this night:</l>
                  <l>For now, methinks, I am prepared for any thing</l>
                  <l>That looks like miſchief.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Damp.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Bravely reſolved.</l>
                  <l>Know then, <hi>Grammount</hi> at preſent</l>
                  <l>Is at the Governours appartment,</l>
                  <l>Where multiplicity of buſineſs,</l>
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:199141:21"/>
                  <l>Committed to his care alone,</l>
                  <l>By the uneaſy <hi>Beaufort,</hi> will certainly</l>
                  <l>Detain him longer than ordinary:</l>
                  <l>So that the Night, which now draws on a pace,</l>
                  <l>Will in all probability be far ſpent,</l>
                  <l>E're he returns to his own Lodgings;</l>
                  <l>And then, then my Girl.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lyſet.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Ay, then will be the time, when I</l>
                  <l>Poor inconſiderable fool, will with</l>
                  <l>Such cunning play my Treacherous part,</l>
                  <l>As ſhall with eaſe impoſe upon the good <hi>Grammount,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Pluck from his faithfull breaſt</l>
                  <l>Deep-rooted Love, and in its room</l>
                  <l>Plant the rank weed of Jealouſie,</l>
                  <l>Turn deareſt Friendſhip into mortal Hate,</l>
                  <l>And ſo give birth to general Confuſion.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Dam.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Revenge, how ſweet thou art! Revenge now makes</l>
                  <l>Thee undertake a part, the Devil himſelf</l>
                  <l>Would bogle at: No Woman ſure e're ſuckled thee,</l>
                  <l>Or ſomething more than man club'd to thy getting.</l>
                  <l>But ſee, the Governour appears,</l>
                  <l>Away, and fail not when it comes to th' puſh</l>
                  <l>Be ſure.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lyſet.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Fear me not.</l>
                  <stage>Exit Lyſet.</stage>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Beaufort.</stage>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Damp.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>This Wench is ripe for Hell.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Beauf.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Well, what News <hi>Dampierre</hi> from <hi>Elvira?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Knows ſhe my Love, does ſhe ſpeak Life or Death?</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Damp.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Hear the ſtory, then be your ſelf the Judge.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Beauf.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Proceed.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Damp.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Know then, that leaving you</l>
                  <l>I went directly to <hi>Elvira</hi>'s Lodgings,</l>
                  <l>But miſſing of her there, and being told,</l>
                  <l>That ſhe was gone, attended by <hi>Lyſette,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>To take a turn i'th Neighbouring Foreſt,</l>
                  <l>Thither I follow'd her, where I firſt met</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Lyſette,</hi> and quickly managed her ſo well,</l>
                  <l>As not to ſtand in awe of her too near</l>
                  <l>Attendance: The Woman ſo ſecured,</l>
                  <l>I boldly ventured to attack the Lady,</l>
                  <l>Whom, as I could have wiſht, I found alone.</l>
                  <l>Our firſt diſcourſe was of indifferent things,</l>
                  <l>Which yet I managed with ſuch curious Art,</l>
                  <l>As drew her on at length to that of Love.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:199141:21"/>
               <speaker>Beauf.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thy boldneſs makes me tremble, <hi>Dampierre.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Damp.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>From Love in general, we quickly came</l>
                  <l>Down to particulars, and then you may</l>
                  <l>Believe I fail'd not to deſcribe your flame</l>
                  <l>As you your ſelf could wiſh.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Beauf.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>nam'd you my name?</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Damp.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Not yet, nor did I at firſt let her know</l>
                  <l>She was the perſon Lov'd: But ſtill mad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </l>
                  <l>Of borrow'd names, till finding that my art</l>
                  <l>Prevail'd, and that the ſoft and moving Terms,</l>
                  <l>In which I told the ſtory of your Love,</l>
                  <l>Had toucht her tender heart with pity of</l>
                  <l>Your caſe, then I reveal'd the ſecret,</l>
                  <l>told her all.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Beauf.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>And how did ſhe receive it ha!</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Damp.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Why Sir, with all the haughty marks of Pride,</l>
                  <l>And Scorn, ſhe could put on; tis true, ſhe ſaid</l>
                  <l>Not much, and fain would have been gone, but I</l>
                  <l>Made bold by the advantage of the place,</l>
                  <l>Stopt her, and would have made her hear me out,</l>
                  <l>When on the ſudden in ſtept—</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Beauf.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Lyſette.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Damp.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>No, Sir, <hi>Montigny.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Beauf.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Montigny</hi> ſay'ſt thou!</l>
                  <l>Hell and Confuſion! but ſay what follow'd.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Damp.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Only this, as ſoon as he appear'd,</l>
                  <l>With eager haſte ſhe flew into his arms,</l>
                  <l>Then with a ſcornful ſmile, and ſlighting toſs</l>
                  <l>O'th' head, ſhe took her leave of me, and ſo</l>
                  <l>Triumphantly went off with her Gallant.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Beauf.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Juſt Gods! How can you wink at ſo much baſe</l>
                  <l>And rank Hypocriſie: If ſuch crimes as theſe</l>
                  <l>Meet with impunity, the world will grow</l>
                  <l>too wicked by the bad example.</l>
                  <l>Rather aſſert, aſſert your Sovereign Power,</l>
                  <l>And darting Thunder at her devoted head,</l>
                  <l>Let her, oh let her unpitied fall</l>
                  <l>A wretched inſtance of offended Juſtice.</l>
                  <l>But, tell me, do'ſt thou believe <hi>Montigny</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Over heard thee?</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Damp.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Moſt certainly he did.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Beauf.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>What then in this unlucky caſe is to be done.</l>
                  <l>For ſure if once <hi>Montigny</hi> knows I love,</l>
                  <l>'Twill not be long a ſecret to <hi>Grammount.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Adviſe me <hi>Dampierre.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:199141:22"/>
               <speaker>Damp.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Excuſe me, Sir, I know no way but one</l>
                  <l>That can effectually ſecure Mens Tongues.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Beauf.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>And what way's that?</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Damp.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Faith, Sir, an eaſy one.</l>
                  <l>Cut but the Throat, the Tongue will tell no tales.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Beauf.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>No, that's a way too rough, I like it not.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Damp.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Why now I think on't better there may be</l>
                  <l>Yet one way more, not quite ſo ſafe perhaps</l>
                  <l>As t'other, but—</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Beauf.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Name it and I am thine</l>
                  <l>For ever, but no blood I charge you.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Damp.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>No, this is a Gentler way, it is but</l>
                  <l>Subtly looſening that firm tie of Friendſhip,</l>
                  <l>Which ſeems ſo well and firmly knit, between</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Montigny</hi> and <hi>Grammount,</hi> and you have done</l>
                  <l>Your buſineſs: For if they are not Friends,</l>
                  <l>Moſt certain 'tis they will be Enemies,</l>
                  <l>There is no mean, and then you need not fear</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Beauf.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Moſt true: but then the difficulty is,</l>
                  <l>How to divide two ſouls ſo ſtrictly, and</l>
                  <l>So long united, in the deareſt bands</l>
                  <l>Of Friendſhip's ſacred, and ſevereſt Laws.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Damp.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Let me alone to manage that affair,</l>
                  <l>If <hi>Grammount</hi> Loves <hi>Elvira,</hi> before</l>
                  <l>To morrows Sun he ſhall as ſurely hate</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Montigny</hi> to the death: Diſtruſt me not,</l>
                  <l>But if you like the project—</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Beauf.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Like it, yes,</l>
                  <l>I gueſs at thy deſign, and like it well:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Grammount</hi> I pity thee, tho' it is but juſt</l>
                  <l>To let thee ſee thy danger, e're thou art</l>
                  <l>Too far impos'd on by a Treacherous friend,</l>
                  <l>And wanton Wife. But it grows late,</l>
                  <l>And I am ſtrangely diſcompoſed. Farewel.</l>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Exit</hi> Beauf.</stage>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Damp.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Go, go to bed old man, ſleep if thou can'ſt,</l>
                  <l>And dream of happy hours thou ne'er ſhalt ſee.</l>
                  <l>So, he's well prepar'd I think, and I have</l>
                  <l>Gain'd a mighty Patron to protect me</l>
                  <l>Whatever miſchief happens; the more</l>
                  <l>the better now, ſince he is like to Anſwer all.</l>
                  <l>Poor I am but his humble Inſtrument,</l>
                  <l>Ha! Ha! Ha!</l>
                  <l>I could e'en kill my ſelf with Laughing now,</l>
                  <l>To ſee how ſtrangely all things have conſpir'd,</l>
                  <l>To Crown my Roguery with Succeſs,</l>
                  <l>And me with Safety.</l>
                  <stage>Exit <hi>Damp.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <stage>
                     <pb facs="tcp:199141:22"/>Enter <hi>Grammount</hi> and a Page before him with a Flambeau.</stage>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gram.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Buſineſs, unlucky buſineſs long has kept</l>
                  <l>Me from <hi>Elvira:</hi> Tho' all late as 'tis,</l>
                  <l>Methinks ſome dark, ill-boding fancy ſeems</l>
                  <l>to tell me, 'tis too early yet, to ſeek</l>
                  <l>Thoſe Joys I ever found in her dear Arms.</l>
                  <l>A ſtrange unuſual damp has ſeized my ſoul,</l>
                  <l>And I who uſe, with eager Joy to fly</l>
                  <l>To my <hi>Elvira,</hi> have now ſcarce the ſtrength,</l>
                  <l>Or Will indeed, to move one ſtep that way.</l>
                  <l>Oh <hi>Dampierre, Dampierre,</hi> what was thy deſign?</l>
                  <l>Since I left thee, my working thoughts have been</l>
                  <l>In a perpetual hurrey; thou, alas!</l>
                  <l>Haſt poyſon'd all my deareſt Joys, and in</l>
                  <l>My troubled mind, laid the foundation</l>
                  <l>Of Eternal Doubts, Perplexing, Gnawing,</l>
                  <l>Killing Doubts. And yet I know thee, <hi>Dampierre,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Baſe, of a Poor, Mean, Low ſpirit too,</l>
                  <l>And ſo, capable of any miſchief.</l>
                  <l>Why then ſhould'ſt thou gain credit with <hi>Grammount,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Who knows thou hat'ſt both him and his <hi>Elvira.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>No, from my memory henceforth I chaſe</l>
                  <l>Thee, and each thought of thy baſe Treachery.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Grammount</hi>'s too happy in a vertuous Wife,</l>
                  <l>And Generous Friend; tho' curſt indeed, in thee,</l>
                  <l>Thou Cruel, and Unatural Brother.</l>
                  <l>But hark, what noiſe is that?</l>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>A noiſe of opening a door and</hi> Lyſette <hi>Enters who ſeeing</hi> Grammount <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends to avoid him. He stops her and turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up her hood ſees her tearing a Letter with her Teeth.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <l>O, 'tis the door opens. Hah!</l>
                  <l>Who art thou that ſtealeſt</l>
                  <l>Away ſo guiltily?</l>
                  <l>Nay, I muſt ſee, <hi>Lyſette!</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Whither away at this</l>
                  <l>Unſeaſonable time of night,</l>
                  <l>And what paper's that thou</l>
                  <l>Mumbleſt ſo?</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lyſet.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Alas! I am undone, Pardon me; ſir,</l>
                  <l>Oh Pardon me I beſeech you.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gram.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Would'ſt have me pard'n thee e're I know thy fault,</l>
                  <l>Confeſs, and then perhaps thou may'ſt deſerve it.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lyſet.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Oh never, never, all that I deſire,</l>
                  <l>Is that you would be ſo juſt, as to believe</l>
                  <l>Me only guilty, for on my life</l>
                  <l>My Lady's innocent.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:199141:23"/>
               <speaker>Gram.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Hah! thy Lady, ſpeak, what of her?</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lyſet.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Why, ſhe I do declare to all the world</l>
                  <l>Is innocent, by all that's good ſhe is,</l>
                  <l>Nay were I to die next minute,</l>
                  <l>My Tongue ſhould end my ſtory with that truth.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gram.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>I ask not of her innocence, but tell me,</l>
                  <l>And tell me truely, as thou hop'ſt for any</l>
                  <l>Mercy from me, whither wert thou</l>
                  <l>Stealing with that Letter, and what</l>
                  <l>Were the contents of it?</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lyſet.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>For Heaven ſake, and for your own, Sir,</l>
                  <l>Preſs me no further, here on my knees</l>
                  <l>I beg you would not.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gram.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Ha! do'ſt thou dally with me?</l>
                  <l>Come, ſpeak quickly, or by heaven thou dieſt.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lyſet.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Do with me what you pleaſe,</l>
                  <l>But force me not, I do beſeech you,</l>
                  <l>To a Confeſſion that—</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gram.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>What! Speak I ſay, tell me,</l>
                  <l>What was that Paper, to whom directed,</l>
                  <l>And from whom?</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lyſet.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Alas I die for fear—</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gram.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>If thou continueſt obſtinate,</l>
                  <l>Not all the world ſhall ſave thee from my Fury.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lyſet.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>It was—</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gram.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>What was it, ſpeak I ſay?</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lyſet.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>It was a Letter—</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gram.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>From whom?</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lyſet.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>It was a Letter from my Lady—</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gram.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Well ſaid, to whom?</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lyſet.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>To—Yet, Sir, excuſe me I conjure you.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gram.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Hah more trifling, out with it boldy, or—</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lyſet.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>'Twas to <hi>Montigny,</hi> Sir,</l>
                  <l>Your beſt, and deareſt friend, <hi>Montigny.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gram.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>To <hi>Montigny!</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Was it to <hi>Montigny,</hi> that <hi>Elvira</hi> ſent thee</l>
                  <l>With that Letter at this unſeaſonable hour?</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lyſet</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>It was: But why ſhould that ſo much diſturb you?</l>
                  <l>A petty quarrel parted 'em in the evening,</l>
                  <l>When tho' <hi>Montigny</hi> humbly ſued for pardon,</l>
                  <l>She would not grant it, till at the laſt, good Lady,</l>
                  <l>Repenting her ſeverity, ſhe could not reſt,</l>
                  <l>Till ſhe had given him an aſſurance, under</l>
                  <l>Her hand, that what he then ſo earneſtly</l>
                  <l>Deſired, was now as freely granted, and—</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:199141:23"/>
               <speaker>Gram.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Peace Screech-Owl,</l>
                  <l>Peace, thou rank meſſenger of luſt:</l>
                  <l>By heaven, I know not why I do not kill thee,</l>
                  <l>Hence from my ſight I ſay, away.</l>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Exit</hi> Lyſette.</stage>
                  <l>But which way now, wretched <hi>Grammount,</hi> wilt thou</l>
                  <l>Direct thy wandring ſteps, where e're thou goeſt,</l>
                  <l>Deſtruction, Horror, and Amazament will attend thee.</l>
                  <l>Thy faithful cares, deaf to all other tales,</l>
                  <l>Will turn each ſound into this one ſad ſtory,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Elvira</hi>'s falſe, <hi>Montigny</hi>'s falſe, and now</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Grammount</hi>'s become, the ſcorn of all the world,</l>
                  <l>Oh 'tis too much for mortal man to bear,</l>
                  <l>By heaven, i'll make my ſad, and juſt Revenge</l>
                  <l>As ſignally notorious as my wrongs.</l>
                  <l>But huſh, be ſtill y' unruly paſſions of</l>
                  <l>My mind, and think <hi>Grammount,</hi> that to revenge</l>
                  <l>is but the way to publiſh thy diſgrace.</l>
                  <l>Patience then, oh patience, grant me juſt heav'n</l>
                  <l>More patience, or take from me that little</l>
                  <l>I am yet maſter of, and in return</l>
                  <l>Bleſs me with madneſs, eternal madneſs,</l>
                  <l>Madneſs without one minutes interval of ſenſe.</l>
                  <l>Grief, Rage, Deſpair poſſeſs my totur'd mind,</l>
                  <l>Make me but mad, ye Gods, and you'll be kind.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <trailer>The end of the fourth Act.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="act">
            <pb n="38" facs="tcp:199141:24"/>
            <head>ACT V. SCENE I.</head>
            <stage>
               <hi>Enter</hi> Elvira <hi>and</hi> Leonora.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Elv.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>NO more, no more; my <hi>Grammount</hi> is unkind,</l>
                  <l>Fickle, inconſtant, wavering, and falſe;</l>
                  <l>Some fatal Beauty has ſurpriz'd his Heart,</l>
                  <l>And chaſed th' unfortunate <hi>Elvira</hi> thence</l>
                  <l>For ever, as a ſtranger to his Love.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Judge not ſo hardly, Madam, of a Flame</l>
                  <l>So pure, ſo exemplary, and ſo chaſte</l>
                  <l>As his.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Elv.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>What other Judgment can I make?</l>
                  <l>In vain I have wept, in vain I have pray'd,</l>
                  <l>In vain all night purſued his flying ſteps</l>
                  <l>From place to place, yet cannot get one Look</l>
                  <l>That may ſeem kind, nor one poor Word</l>
                  <l>By which I might but gueſs at the ſad Cauſe</l>
                  <l>Of his pretended Grief.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>This his proceeding</l>
                  <l>Seems to me moſt ſtrange, I muſt confeſs,</l>
                  <l>But yet—</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Elv.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Seek not, dear <hi>Leonora,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>To excuſe him, but rather pity me.</l>
                  <l>Ah! hadſt thou been a Witneſs of my grief,</l>
                  <l>And of thoſe rough returns he laſt night made</l>
                  <l>To all the ſofteſt and engaging Arts</l>
                  <l>My Love could then invent, or his deſire,</l>
                  <l>Thou wouldſt with Tears lament, not doubt his change.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>What ſtrange Unkindneſs was he guilty of!</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Elv.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Long had I wiſht my dear <hi>Grammount</hi>'s return,</l>
                  <l>With all th' impatience of a loving Wife,</l>
                  <l>Ready to ſhare and ſooth his neareſt Cares,</l>
                  <l>And lull his wearied Body in theſe Arms</l>
                  <l>To gentle Reſt. The Night far ſpent, at length</l>
                  <l>He came; but when with open Arms I ran</l>
                  <l>To meet him, alas! how was I ſurpriz'd,</l>
                  <l>When I read nought but Fury in his Face!</l>
                  <l>Doubting his Health, and vent'ring yet nearer</l>
                  <l>To him, he frown'd, and rudely flung me off:</l>
                  <l>Yet by degrees his Rage began to waſte;</l>
                  <l>And giving place to ſome more gentle Thoughts,</l>
                  <l>A fullen deadly Grief ſeem'd to ſucceed it:</l>
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:199141:24"/>
                  <l>When I, once more, attempting to draw near,</l>
                  <l>He gently only put me by, then with</l>
                  <l>A deep and diſmal ſigh turn'd ſhort away,</l>
                  <l>Leaving me all in tears, and almoſt dead</l>
                  <l>With grief. Yet I reſolv'd to follow him;</l>
                  <l>And ſo indeed we paſs'd the tedious Night,</l>
                  <l>He flying ſtill, I ſtill purſuing, tho' in vain.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>With all my Heart I pity you, and wiſh</l>
                  <l>Twere in my power to ſerve you, Madam.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Elv.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Ah, my dear Child, what can thy Kindneſs do</l>
                  <l>For miſerable me, unleſs perhaps</l>
                  <l>It teach thee now to bear me company</l>
                  <l>In tears, to echo forth my ſighs from thy</l>
                  <l>Compaſſionate Breaſt, and kindly ſhare</l>
                  <l>The ſharpeſt Pangs of a too juſt Deſpair?</l>
                  <l>All this, my Dear, I dare expect from thee,</l>
                  <l>And from thy Love; and yet even all this</l>
                  <l>Would but augment, not eaſe my Miſery.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Yet ſomething more I'll do, I'll to <hi>Grammount,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And force that fatal Secret from his Breaſt,</l>
                  <l>Which he yet keeps ſo cloſe.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Elv.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>But can you think.</l>
                  <l>That he will hear a Siſter, who is deaf</l>
                  <l>To all the ſighs of a once dear-lov'd Wife?</l>
                  <l>No, no; too much you wrong my dear <hi>Grammount<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Were he the Man he was, with Joy he'd hear</l>
                  <l>His dear <hi>Elvira;</hi> but not being ſo,</l>
                  <l>Be yet ſo juſt as to believe him deaf</l>
                  <l>To all the World beſide, as well as her.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Whither will your diſtemper'd Fancy lead</l>
                  <l>You, Madam? Oh, think—</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Elv.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Alas, I know not.</l>
                  <l>Ah my <hi>Grammount!</hi> couldſt thou but gueſs to what</l>
                  <l>A wretched ſtate thy cruel uſage has</l>
                  <l>Reduc'd the poor unfortunate <hi>Elvira,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>'Twould make thee ſoon repent, and give new life</l>
                  <l>To thy expiring Love.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Madam, once more</l>
                  <l>I do beſeech you give me leave to try</l>
                  <l>My Fortune with <hi>Grammount;</hi> I may prevail.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Elv.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Never: alas, he will deſpiſe thy Sex,</l>
                  <l>And ſlight thy tender age. No, were he to be</l>
                  <l>Prevail'd on by Entreaties, <hi>Montigny</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Beſt of all the World might hope to do it.</l>
                  <l>But—</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:199141:25"/>
               <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Deſpair not, Madam, Friendſhip, perhaps,</l>
                  <l>May do what Love at preſent cannot.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Elv.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Ah, tempt me not to entertain a Hope</l>
                  <l>Which, once deceiv'd, will but encreaſe my Pain.</l>
                  <l>Yet for thy ſake, my Dear, I do ſubmit.</l>
                  <l>Go to <hi>Montigny</hi> then, and faithfully</l>
                  <l>Relate my Story; but leave the reſt to him,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe Generoſity will better teach</l>
                  <l>Him how to act, than all that we can ſay.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Madam, I fly.</l>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Exit</hi> Leon.</stage>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Elv.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>And I in the mean time will once more ſeek</l>
                  <l>My Dear, my falſe, ungrateful Fugitive</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Grammount.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Exit</hi> Elvira.</stage>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Dampierre <hi>and</hi> Lyſette.</stage>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Damp.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Well met; what News, my little Fury,</l>
                  <l>From thy Quarters?</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lyſ.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>News, my great Lord of Miſchief, worthy of</l>
                  <l>Thy Ear. In ſhort, I've play'd my part</l>
                  <l>Moſt rarely well, and now the Devil, I think,</l>
                  <l>Is playing his.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Damp.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>As how, I pray? What, is the wiſe virtuous</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Grammount</hi> caught at laſt? Does he begin to powt?</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lyſ.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Oh, extreamly.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Damp.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>And <hi>Elvira,</hi> what does ſhe? ha!</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lyſ.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Why, ſhe e'en whines, and pines, and blubbers,</l>
                  <l>Like any o'ergrown Girl that had been</l>
                  <l>Newly whipt.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Damp.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Good, wondrous good.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lyſ.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Yes, yes; all yet goes wondrous well indeed;</l>
                  <l>But what the end will be, for my part,</l>
                  <l>I cannot gueſs.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Damp.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>No matter, let there be no end at all,</l>
                  <l>But that which puts an end to all things, Death.</l>
                  <l>Oh, may Confuſion, Rage, Deſpair, and</l>
                  <l>Everlaſting Jealouſie attend 'em to their Graves.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lyſ.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Amen, ſay I: but yet ſuppoſe they ſhould</l>
                  <l>At laſt come to a right Underſtanding,</l>
                  <l>What would become of me, I pray?</l>
                  <l>Were it not better, think you, to decamp</l>
                  <l>In time, and leave them to themſelves?</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Damp.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>By no means; that would make 'em preſently</l>
                  <l>Smell out thy Roguery and their own Error:</l>
                  <l>Rather be more diligent, and more aſſiduous</l>
                  <l>In your attendance now than ever:</l>
                  <l>Conſult their Looks, for till you find the weather</l>
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:199141:25"/>
                  <l>Clearing there, you need not fear a Storm;</l>
                  <l>And then at laſt it will be time enough to fly.</l>
                  <l>In the mean time, here; thou haſt been</l>
                  <stage>Offers a pair of Gloves.</stage>
                  <l>Induſtrious, and doſt deſerve Encouragement.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lyſ.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>A naſty dirty pair of Gloves, I warrant you;</l>
                  <l>Foh! I'll have none of 'em.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Damp.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Away, thou'rt a Fool, and knowſt not what</l>
                  <l>Thou haſt refus'd: they are, I tell thee,</l>
                  <l>Gloves of the richeſt ſcent; beſides, each Finger's</l>
                  <l>Lin'd with Gold; here, wear 'em for my ſake.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lyſ.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Well, for once I care not if I do, the cordial Gold</l>
                  <l>Perhaps may keep my Spirits up, and give me</l>
                  <l>Strength to bear the brunt of all. Adieu, Sir.</l>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Exit</hi> Lyſ.</stage>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Damp.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Go thy ways, thou art a dainty Girl, and doſt love</l>
                  <l>Miſchief well, for which I love thee, tho' I dare not</l>
                  <l>Truſt thee. Thou art indeed a thought too mercenary,</l>
                  <l>And may'ſt at laſt, for Gold, ſell me, as thou already haſt</l>
                  <l>Thy Miſtreſs; therefore I can but pity thee. Thoſe Gloves,</l>
                  <l>How rich ſoe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>er and ſweet their ſcent may ſeem,</l>
                  <l>Yet once well heated on the Hand, will caſt a ſtrong</l>
                  <l>And deadly ſmell, moſt fatal to the Brain, a Poyſon</l>
                  <l>Not only certain, but ſtrangely ſudden in its operation,</l>
                  <l>As I was told, at leaſt, by an <hi>Italian</hi> famous in that helliſh</l>
                  <l>Art, from whom I had 'em. If it be ſo, my buſineſs is</l>
                  <l>Compleatly done, and thou, poor fool, <hi>Lyſette,</hi> haſt</l>
                  <l>The Reward of all thy Services.</l>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Exit</hi> Damp.</stage>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Grammount.</stage>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gram.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>What is that thing call'd Happineſs, which Men</l>
                  <l>With ſo much noiſe and eager zeal purſue</l>
                  <l>So many ſeveral ways, each hoping to</l>
                  <l>Attain it in the poſſeſſion of ſome</l>
                  <l>Diſtant long'd-for Bleſſing, tho' all alike</l>
                  <l>In vain? For even that darling Bleſſing</l>
                  <l>Plac'd in a nearer light, and once enjoy'd,</l>
                  <l>Loſes but too much of its wonted luſtre;</l>
                  <l>Or elſe, encounter'd with rude Croſſes from</l>
                  <l>Abroad, is loſt and buried in a thick</l>
                  <l>And diſmal Cloud of rank uneaſie Cares.</l>
                  <l>There's no ſuch thing then as a happy man</l>
                  <l>On this ſide of the Grave. Look on me, all</l>
                  <l>You vain Pretenders, look on me, and own</l>
                  <l>At laſt this Truth; for all the deareſt Joys</l>
                  <l>Of Life did ſeem to court and flatter me:</l>
                  <l>Yet all thoſe Joys are in one moment dampt,</l>
                  <l>All vaniſht, all loſt to me for ever.</l>
                  <pb n="42" facs="tcp:199141:26"/>
                  <l>Friendſhip and Love, which once made up</l>
                  <l>The ſweeteſt part of 'em, do now conſpire</l>
                  <l>My ruin. Oh <hi>Elvira!</hi>
                  </l>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Elvira.</stage>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Elv.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Oh <hi>Grammount!</hi>
                  </l>
                  <stage>He turns from her.</stage>
                  <l>Nay, turn not, turn not, cruel man, away,</l>
                  <l>But look upon thy poor diſconſolate</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Elvira,</hi> almoſt drown<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>d in tears: ſpeak,</l>
                  <l>Oh ſpeak at laſt, and let her know wherein</l>
                  <l>She has been faulty or unfortunate</l>
                  <l>Enough to merit this hard uſage from</l>
                  <l>Her much-lov'd <hi>Grammount.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gram.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Art thou <hi>Elvira?</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Elv.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Why doſt thou ask that unkind Queſtion?</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gram.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Becauſe <hi>Elvira</hi> ever loved <hi>Grammount,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And ſo could never be a trouble to him.</l>
                  <l>But thou, alas! art moſt importunate;</l>
                  <l>Prithee be gone, thou art not <hi>Elvira,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Not the ſame <hi>Elvira,</hi> that I'm ſure of.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Elv.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Yes, I am the very ſame I ever was,</l>
                  <l>The very ſame <hi>Elvira</hi> ſtill, on whom</l>
                  <l>With deareſt Tranſports thou didſt once beſtow</l>
                  <l>Ten thouſand Vows of everlaſting Love:</l>
                  <l>The ſame unfortunate <hi>Elvira<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Who, charm'd by thy ſweet, ſoft, bewitching Arts,</l>
                  <l>Heard with delight thoſe many treacherous Vows</l>
                  <l>By thee intended for her ruine.</l>
                  <l>In ſhort, I am the ſame <hi>Elvira</hi> that</l>
                  <l>At laſt crown'd all thy hopes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> paying down Love</l>
                  <l>For Love, as I then thought, tho' ſince I find,</l>
                  <l>With pureſt Gold I only purchas<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>d Droſs.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gram.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Forbear, forbear <hi>Elvira,</hi> and recall</l>
                  <l>Not to my Memory thoſe happy days</l>
                  <l>In which I dearly lov'd, and thou wert kind;</l>
                  <l>Too much, alas! 'twill aggravate my Grief,</l>
                  <l>Since I within this Breaſt already feel</l>
                  <l>Torments, to which nothing, I'm ſure, can add</l>
                  <l>New Pains, but a reflection on that Heaven</l>
                  <l>I once en<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oyed in thee and thy dear Love.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>If in <hi>Elvira</hi>'s Love thou once wert bleſt,</l>
                  <l>Why art thou not ſo ſtill<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gram.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Oh <hi>Elvira!</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>All things <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>e ſtrangely alter'd ſince that time;</l>
                  <l>Love once was pure, and Friendſhip ſacred held,</l>
                  <l>Yet now the one is little elſe but Luſt,</l>
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:199141:26"/>
                  <l>The other all deſign. Vertue is fled,</l>
                  <l>And Vice Reigns now Triumphant in each ſex,</l>
                  <l>We are all wond'rous weak alas, and frail. Oh—</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Elv.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>'Tis true, moſt true my dear <hi>Grammount,</hi> and yet</l>
                  <l>What weakneſs canſt thou juſtly tax me with;</l>
                  <l>Unleſs perhaps my loving thee too well,</l>
                  <l>Be an infirmity unpardonable</l>
                  <l>In the unfortunate <hi>Elvira.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gram.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Oh—</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Elv.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Alas! what means that ſad and diſmal groan,</l>
                  <l>By grief extorted from thy manly breaſt:</l>
                  <l>Thou canſt not ſure be ſo unjuſt, as to</l>
                  <l>Suſpect my Love. Yet if thou art, ſpeak</l>
                  <l>I conjure thee, but ſpeak plainly then,</l>
                  <l>And not in un-intelligible groans.</l>
                  <l>Speak, cruel man, oh ſpeak, do I not love thee?</l>
                  <l>Am I falſe? oh may <hi>Elvira</hi> live no longer,</l>
                  <l>Than with a paſſion Innocent and Pure</l>
                  <l>She loves her dear <hi>Grammount.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gram.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>What pity 'tis our hearts are not expos'd</l>
                  <l>To open view, as are our faces, that</l>
                  <l>So, even our moſt private thoughts might all</l>
                  <l>Appear, naked and bear as at their firſt</l>
                  <l>Conception, e're dreſt up in ornamental</l>
                  <l>Words, of a much different import.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Elv.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Ah, could'ſt thou but ſee into my heart,</l>
                  <l>Thou there would'ſt ſoon perceive thy error</l>
                  <l>And my innocence. But ſince, my dear <hi>Grammount,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>That cannot be, believe my words, believe</l>
                  <l>Theſe tears, believe my Actions, oh ſee,</l>
                  <l>I am here ready to receive thee ſtill,</l>
                  <l>Rude and Unkind, Ungrateful and Inhumane</l>
                  <l>As thou art. Come then, come to theſe arms,</l>
                  <l>Ne're yet ſtretcht out to thee in vain.</l>
                  <l>Wilt thou not come, not yet? thou canſt not ſure</l>
                  <l>Deny me now, when all I beg of thee,</l>
                  <l>Is, that once more thou would'ſt be happy.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gram.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Why ſhould'ſt thou deſire impoſſibilities?</l>
                  <l>Alas! I never can be happy more.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Elv.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>If thou <hi>Grammount</hi> can'ſt ne're be happy more,</l>
                  <l>Then muſt I be for ever miſerable.</l>
                  <l>Cruel man, ſhew yet ſome ſmall remainder</l>
                  <l>Of humanity; be not ſo raſh,</l>
                  <l>Either accuſe, or elſe acquit me,</l>
                  <l>But paſs not ſentence on me e're I'm heard,</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:199141:27"/>
               <speaker>Gram.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>No, fear not too haſty, or too hard</l>
                  <l>A ſentence from my mouth. Falſe as thou art,</l>
                  <l>I cannot hate, where once I loved ſo well.</l>
                  <l>Live then <hi>Elvira,</hi> live long, but live a</l>
                  <l>Stranger to <hi>Grammount.</hi> And that thou may'ſt live</l>
                  <l>Happily, wipe from thy memory the</l>
                  <l>Deareſt paſſages of ſome few paſt years,</l>
                  <l>And ſee thou quite forget, there e're was ſuch</l>
                  <l>A wretch i'th' world as I am.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Elv.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Hold, oh hold!</l>
                  <l>It is too much, alas! inſult not poorly</l>
                  <l>O're my weakneſs, nor play the wanton</l>
                  <l>With my grief: Why do'ſt thou bid me live,</l>
                  <l>I fit muſt be without <hi>Grammount?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Why do'ſt thou wiſh me happy? when all my happineſs,</l>
                  <l>Thou know'ſt depends upon thy love,</l>
                  <l>Yet that thou ſay'ſt is forfeited, is loſt</l>
                  <l>To me for ever, oh my <hi>Grammount.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>It is emiff thou art unkind,</l>
                  <l>Be not unjuſt to thy <hi>Elvira.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>For pities ſake grant ſomething to the dear</l>
                  <l>Memory of our mutual Love,</l>
                  <l>And if thou know'ſt me falſe, tell me wherein,</l>
                  <l>When, or with whom I have offended.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gram.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>What ſatisfaction would it be to thee</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Elvira,</hi> ſhould I tell thee all: ſince all</l>
                  <l>Alas! can be no more, than what thou know'ſt,</l>
                  <l>As well at leaſt, if not much better than</l>
                  <l>My ſelf. In ſhort, I am convinced thou can'ſt not</l>
                  <l>Clear thy ſelf; and if ſo, conſider that</l>
                  <l>A weak defence is worſe than none at all.</l>
                  <l>Tempt me not then to ſpeak, ſince 'twill but add</l>
                  <l>To thy Confuſion, and my Shame:</l>
                  <l>But I would willingly ſpare both, as much</l>
                  <l>As may be with my honour.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Elv.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Confuſion,</l>
                  <l>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>me, Contempt, and everlaſting Infamy,</l>
                  <l>For ever be my Lot, if e're I wronged</l>
                  <l>Thy Love ſo much as in one guilty thought.</l>
                  <l>Oh my <hi>Grammount</hi> my dear, my Lov'd <hi>Grammount,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>See thy <hi>Elvira</hi> o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> her tender knees,</l>
                  <l>From whence ſhe ne're will riſe, till ſhe has learnt</l>
                  <l>The ſtrange and fatal cauſe of her diſgrace.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gram.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Away, this thy affected obſtinacy,</l>
                  <l>Would make me hate thee, were it poſſible.</l>
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:199141:27"/>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Elvira,</hi> is it not enough that thou haſt</l>
                  <l>Wrong'd my Honour? but that I my ſelf</l>
                  <l>Muſt here repeat the ſhameful Tale</l>
                  <l>Only to gratifie thy wanton curioſity.</l>
                  <l>Perhaps indeed, I know not half thy brave</l>
                  <l>Exploits, ſo my imperfect tale may yeild.</l>
                  <l>Thee ſome diverſion: But have a care,</l>
                  <l>The Cuckold yet bears his misfortune</l>
                  <l>Patiently enough, make him not then thy ſport,</l>
                  <l>For if thou do'ſt, by Heaven away, away</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Elvira,</hi> I would not be provokt, away I ſay,</l>
                  <l>Whilſt yet I'm Maſter of my growing Paſſion.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Elv.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Do what thou wilt, be rude, be cruel,</l>
                  <l>Be inhuman as thou haſt been, to the Poor</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Elvira,</hi> yet whilſt ſhe has any ſtrength,</l>
                  <l>She never will let go this hold, unleſs</l>
                  <l>Thou firſt communicate the fatal ſecret.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gram.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Away, thou'lt force me to be rude.</l>
                  <l>Be not ſo ſtrangely obſtinate, alas!</l>
                  <l>I would be civil, tho I can't be kind.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Elv.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Barbarous man! yet ſpeak, what have I done?</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gram.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Will nothing elſe content thee? then thus</l>
                  <l>I throw thee off, and force my way.</l>
                  <stage>Strives to get from her, and drags her about the Stage.</stage>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Elv.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>And thus</l>
                  <l>I cling to thee, cloſe as the tender Ivie</l>
                  <l>To the ſturdy Elm. Do, do mercileſs</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Grammount,</hi> do, pull, hale, tear, drag, nay kill me,</l>
                  <l>Yet I'll not willingly let go: But oh!</l>
                  <l>His cruel ſtrength prevails.</l>
                  <stage>He breaks from her.</stage>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gram.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Farewell thou moſt importunate of Women.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Elv.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Stay, ſtay my <hi>Grammount,</hi> give me but one poor</l>
                  <l>Minute more, and all is done: Fear not,</l>
                  <l>I will no longer urge my innocence,</l>
                  <l>It is enough that thou believeſt me falſe:</l>
                  <l>Oh, for thy own repoſe, may'ſt thou for ever</l>
                  <l>Think me ſo. Farewell, methinks I feel,</l>
                  <l>My lab'ring ſoul ſtriving, and ſtrug'ling,</l>
                  <l>With its utmoſt force, to break it's wretched</l>
                  <l>Priſon, yet ſomething, I know not what, ſtill</l>
                  <l>Makes reſiſtance and obſtructs its paſſage.</l>
                  <l>I ſee <hi>Grammount,</hi> thou likeſt not the delay,</l>
                  <l>I will diſpatch then, and for thy ſake,</l>
                  <l>Haſten the ſlow approaches of my fate.</l>
                  <l>Art thou then fled, art thou then gone for ever?</l>
                  <pb n="46" facs="tcp:199141:28"/>
                  <l>Farewel my dear, unkind, <hi>Grammount,</hi> farewell</l>
                  <l>And when I'm dead, think what the poor <hi>Elvira</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Would have done to have kept thy love, who on</l>
                  <l>Her own tender breaſt dares thus revenge</l>
                  <l>The fatal loſs.</l>
                  <stage>She pulls out a Dagger and ſtabs her ſelf.</stage>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gram.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Hold, hold, <hi>Elvira</hi> hold!</l>
                  <l>By Heaven 'twas boldly done, and nothing could</l>
                  <l>Have given ſo ſure a blow but Innocence</l>
                  <l>It ſelf. Yes my <hi>Elvira,</hi> every drop</l>
                  <l>Of that dear blood, loudly procliams to all</l>
                  <l>The world, thy innocence and my ſad guilt.</l>
                  <l>Oh ye juſt powers above! to what ſtrange fate</l>
                  <l>Am I at length reſerved! ſee, at thy feet</l>
                  <l>My dear <hi>Elvira,</hi> the wretched'ſt thing alive,</l>
                  <l>A thing, unworthy of the name of Man,</l>
                  <l>A Penitent, who dares not hope for pardon</l>
                  <l>Either from Heaven or thee, tho both alas!</l>
                  <l>Are infinitly good, and merciful.</l>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Montigny.</stage>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mont.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Where is <hi>Grammount,</hi> where is my deareſt Friend?</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gram.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Who is it names <hi>Grammount,</hi> hah!</l>
                  <stage>Starting up.</stage>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mont.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Elvira</hi> all in blood! Oh Heavens!</l>
                  <l>I hardly dare believe my Eyes, what wretch</l>
                  <l>Could have the heart to do ſo Villanous</l>
                  <l>A deed?</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gram.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>See here that miſerable wretch,</l>
                  <l>That bloody Villain thou waſt ſpeaking of.</l>
                  <l>He was thy friend, oh, if thou ſtill art his,</l>
                  <l>Do him one friendly office, draw, and ſheath</l>
                  <l>Thy Sword in this diſloyal Breaſt; ſtrike home</l>
                  <l>Be ſure, and with one kind obliging blow</l>
                  <l>At once deliver me, from the too juſt</l>
                  <l>Reproaches of the world, from this dear, yet</l>
                  <l>Killing ſpectacle, and from my hated ſelf.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Elv.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>This wound, believe me, came not from his hand,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Elvira</hi>'s arm, aſſiſted by diſpair,</l>
                  <l>Had ſtrength enough to give the fatal blow.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mont.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Oh my <hi>Grammount,</hi> oh my dear friend,</l>
                  <l>What a vaſt Treaſure haſt thou loſt.</l>
                  <l>Alas! what can I do but pity thee,</l>
                  <l>Thy crime carries its own puniſhment</l>
                  <l>Along with it, a puniſhment beyond</l>
                  <l>What the ſevereſt juſtice can inflict.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <stage>
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:199141:28"/>
               <hi>Enter</hi> Beaufort</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Beauf.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Tell me what means this general mourning,</l>
                  <l>A ſad confuſion ſeems to reign within</l>
                  <l>Theſe walls, where e're I go I meet with deep</l>
                  <l>Deſpair, and if I chance to ask the cauſe,</l>
                  <l>I'm anſwered only with a ſigh, ſome tears,</l>
                  <l>And a diſtracted ghaſtly look, and that</l>
                  <l>Is all th' intelligence I can get.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gram.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Here be informed then, oh ſee here a Sight,</l>
                  <l>Will ſhake thy generous ſoul with horror:</l>
                  <l>A Sight, will make even thee look pale,</l>
                  <l>And tremble, tho' long ennured to ſlaughter,</l>
                  <l>And brought up in blood. Nay, ſtart not Sir,</l>
                  <l>It is <hi>Elvira</hi> welt'ring in her gore,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Elvira</hi> fal'n by her own hand,</l>
                  <l>But murdered by <hi>Grammount.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Leonora.</stage>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Never did ſo much joy, as here I bring</l>
                  <l>Spring from ſo ſad a cauſe.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Beauf.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Hah! who's that unſeaſonably mentions joy</l>
                  <l>Here in this place of everlaſting Woe.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Oh heavens! are all my deareſt hopes thus daſht?</l>
                  <l>Oh Madam, who has done this bloody deed?</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Elv.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>'Twas I, 'twas I my ſelf<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> my dear, weep not</l>
                  <l>For me, but rather go, and comfort</l>
                  <l>If thou canſt the poor <hi>Grammount.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Oh <hi>Grammount!</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Unfortunate <hi>Grammount,</hi> moſt groſly haſt</l>
                  <l>Thou been impoſed on, ſtrangely abuſed</l>
                  <l>By that prodigious Monſter <hi>Dampierre.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Know then, that Letter, thought directed</l>
                  <l>By <hi>Elvira</hi> to <hi>Montigny,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And ſent, at that dead guilty time of night,</l>
                  <l>Was but a trick, a meer device, the whole,</l>
                  <l>Only a ſcene contrived by <hi>Dampierre,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Acted by <hi>Lyſette.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>This truth, from her own mouth I juſt now learnt,</l>
                  <l>And ſhe confirmed it with her lateſt breath.</l>
                  <l>For ſhe is dead, poyſoned by <hi>Dampierre.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>This confeſſion was to me, I muſt confeſs,</l>
                  <l>Moſt welcome, and welcome ſure it would have been</l>
                  <pb n="48" facs="tcp:199141:29"/>
                  <l>To all, had it been made but ſome few minutes</l>
                  <l>Sooner.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gram.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Gods! what has this miſerable Caitif done.</l>
                  <l>To draw down all your anger on his head?</l>
                  <l>What horrid crimes before had ſtained his Soul</l>
                  <l>That you ſhould thus, all at one fatal blow,</l>
                  <l>Oppreſs the wretch with your ſevereſt Judgments?</l>
                  <l>Oh, that ſome Mountain now would fall on me,</l>
                  <l>And in its dreadful ruines hide my head.</l>
                  <l>But hark methinks the Gods grow loud; hark, how</l>
                  <l>Their awful thunder grumbles in the Sky,</l>
                  <l>See how the fiery balls fly whizzing by!</l>
                  <l>Dealing amazement, and deſtruction all a round.</l>
                  <l>Ha, ha, ha, ha.</l>
                  <l>See you old miſer, laden with ſwelling bags</l>
                  <l>Of ill-got Gold, with how much awkar'd haſte,</l>
                  <l>He limps away to ſhelter: ſee how he ducks,</l>
                  <l>And dives, and dodges with the Gods, and all</l>
                  <l>Only in hope t' avoid, for ſome few daies</l>
                  <l>Perhaps, the juſt reward of his accurſed extortion.</l>
                  <l>The hot Adulterer now, all chill and impotent</l>
                  <l>With fear, leaps from the polluted bed,</l>
                  <l>And crams himſelf into a cranny,</l>
                  <l>Thoſe mighty men of blood, who make a Trade</l>
                  <l>Of murder, forget their wonted fierceneſs:</l>
                  <l>Outnois'd they ſhrink aſide, and ſhake for fear</l>
                  <l>O'th' louder threatnings of the angry Gods.</l>
                  <l>Whilſt I, I only, tho' the wickedeſt wre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ch of all,</l>
                  <l>with an erected countenance ſtand to't,</l>
                  <l>Courting thoſe dangers others ſeek to avoid.</l>
                  <l>And yet there's not one dart one ball for me,</l>
                  <l>Tho I, Heaven knows, deſerve 'em all. Oh</l>
                  <stage>He throws himſelf on the ground.</stage>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Elv.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Let not the knowledge of my innocence,</l>
                  <l>My dear <hi>Grammount,</hi> add to thy grief,</l>
                  <l>Rather believe me guilty ſtill, alas!</l>
                  <l>Thy generous eaſy nature was abuſed,</l>
                  <l>Impoſed on by a Brothers wicked arts.</l>
                  <l>Thou ſtill art innocent, and ſo am I,</l>
                  <l>Who freely can forgive thy greateſt faults.</l>
                  <l>Come then <hi>Grammount,</hi> come to thy <hi>Elvira,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And with a kiſs, a cold and dying kiſs,</l>
                  <l>I'll ſeal thy pardon.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gram.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>My dear <hi>Elvira,</hi> this thy prodigious</l>
                  <l>Goodneſs, does but encreaſe my miſery.</l>
                  <l>Yet I will come, yes my <hi>Elvira,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb n="49" facs="tcp:199141:29"/>
                  <l>With a down dejected countenance,</l>
                  <l>Not daring to look up, but creeping thus,</l>
                  <l>And crawling on the earth, I do approach</l>
                  <l>Thy feet, here, ſpurn the vile thing, tread, trample</l>
                  <l>The miſerable inſect into nothing.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Elv.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Oh my <hi>Grammount,</hi> yield not too much to grief.</l>
                  <l>It is a fatal, tho a ſlow diſeaſe.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gram.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>I thank thee, dear <hi>Elvira,</hi> for that hint.</l>
                  <l>Now thou art kind, and giv'ſt me good advice.</l>
                  <l>Whoever would endure an age of pain,</l>
                  <l>When one ſuch blow as this, might give him preſent eaſe?</l>
                  <stage>Stabbs himſelf.</stage>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Beauf.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Hold, oh hold <hi>Grammount.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Oh heavens what has he done?</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mont.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Too much alas! altho' no more than what</l>
                  <l>I apprehended from his juſt deſpair.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gram.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Help me, my friend, and place me near that Saint.</l>
                  <l>So, now 'tis pretty well, pardon me my dear</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Elvira,</hi> that ſo long I have defer'd</l>
                  <l>This piece of Juſtice, or rather pardon me,</l>
                  <l>That at laſt I durſt preſume to mingle.</l>
                  <l>My polluted blood, with thoſe pure ſtreams of thine.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Elv.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Oh my <hi>Grammount!</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>My Love can pardon thee any thing,</l>
                  <l>Yet 'twas unkind, to give me thus</l>
                  <l>A ſecond wound, a wound more grievous</l>
                  <l>To the poor <hi>Elvira,</hi> than the firſt</l>
                  <l>Which gave her death.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Elv.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Where, where art thou my <hi>Grammount</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>A riſing miſt has on a ſudden ſnatched</l>
                  <l>Thee from my ſight, alas! I faint, I dye,</l>
                  <l>Death ſeizes now on every part, and my</l>
                  <l>Affrighted Soul ſits hovering on my pale</l>
                  <l>And trembling lips, juſt ready to begin</l>
                  <l>Its flight.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gram.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Oh ſtay, <hi>Elvira,</hi> for thy dear <hi>Grammount,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Stay yet, but one poor minute, then,</l>
                  <l>As we have long liv'd and lov'd,</l>
                  <l>So let us ſtill Love, and lanch together</l>
                  <l>Into a vaſt eternity, where we may Love</l>
                  <l>For ever.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Elv.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Oh no, imperious death commands</l>
                  <l>And I muſt needs obey. But do thou live,</l>
                  <l>Live yet, if it be poſſible, and Love</l>
                  <l>The memory of the poor <hi>Elvira,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Farewel—Farewel—my dear <hi>Grammount</hi>—For ever</l>
                  <stage>She dies.</stage>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:199141:30"/>
               <speaker>Gram.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>She's gone, and all my comfort is, that I</l>
                  <l>Shall quickly follow her. Yes, this ſight wounds</l>
                  <l>Deeper than the ſharpeſt dagger. And yet</l>
                  <l>How many Charms remain Unconquer'd ſtill,</l>
                  <l>As Beauty lies Triumphant over Fate,</l>
                  <l>And ſeems to flouriſh in the arms of death.</l>
                  <l>Oh let me ſteal one parting kiſs, at leaſt,</l>
                  <l>From thoſe cold lips.</l>
                  <l>But e're I go, my Friend</l>
                  <l>On thee I here beſtow all I have left</l>
                  <l>Of value in the world, this weeping Maid.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mont.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>If the fair <hi>Leonora</hi> will confirm</l>
                  <l>The gift, I ſhall be but too happy.</l>
                  <l>Oh, my <hi>Grammount</hi> I beg thee to believe</l>
                  <l>Since Fate deprives me of my deareſt Friend,</l>
                  <l>Nought but ſo rich a preſent from his hand</l>
                  <l>Could bribe me to ſurvive ſo ſenſible a loſs,</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gram.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Here take her then.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Beauf.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>And with her all my wealth,</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gram.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>The poor <hi>Grammount</hi> can only thank you Sir.</l>
                  <l>Come <hi>Leonora</hi>—</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>For Heavens ſake—</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gram.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>This modeſty's unſeaſonable now.</l>
                  <l>Deny me not the ſatisfaction</l>
                  <l>To ſee thee e're I die ſo well beſtowed,</l>
                  <l>Give me thy hand. Take her <hi>Montigny.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And may this ſaithful Wiſe abundantly</l>
                  <l>Supply the want of an Unfortunate</l>
                  <l>But real Friend—</l>
                  <l>Farewel! a long farewel to all. Hark, hark</l>
                  <l>Methinks I hear <hi>Elvira</hi> call. I come,</l>
                  <l>I come <hi>Elvira,</hi> my aſpiring Soul</l>
                  <l>Begins to mount, not to o'retake, but at</l>
                  <l>An awful diſtance to attend and wait</l>
                  <l>On thine above, in thoſe bleſt Regions</l>
                  <l>Of eternal peace.</l>
                  <stage>He dies</stage>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Beauf.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Fate now has done its worſt, and from me torn</l>
                  <l>All the delight and comfort of my age.</l>
                  <l>Who waits there? hah!</l>
                  <stage>Enter Servants at one door, <hi>Damp,</hi> at the other.</stage>
                  <l>But ſee, juſt Heaven has ſent him to receive</l>
                  <l>The due reward of all his crimes. Seize,</l>
                  <l>Seize on that Villain <hi>Dampierre</hi> inſtantly.</l>
                  <stage>they ſeize him.</stage>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Damp.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>What means this rudeneſs, hah!</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Beauf.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Look there, <hi>Grammount</hi> is dead, <hi>Elvira</hi>'s dead,</l>
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:199141:30"/>
                  <l>And all this miſchief is but the effect</l>
                  <l>Of thy black helliſh arts.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Damp.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Why, if they are dead,</l>
                  <l>Let 'em be buried: What is't to me?</l>
                  <l>They might have longer lived, or ſooner died</l>
                  <l>For ought I know, who is it dares blame me?</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>I, tho thy Siſter, muſt accuſe thee wretch</l>
                  <l>Think, think on <hi>Lyſette,</hi> poyſoned by thee,</l>
                  <l>She with her lateſt breath diſcovered all</l>
                  <l>Thy arts.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Damp.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Then my <hi>Italian</hi> was a Raſcal,</l>
                  <l>Away, thou art a Girl, and ſhould'ſt be whipt</l>
                  <l>For prating.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Ah! was't not enough, that in the Foreſt</l>
                  <l>Thou on <hi>Elvira</hi>'s honour madeſt a baſe</l>
                  <l>Attempt, but to reward her goodneſs</l>
                  <l>In concealing thy black crime,</l>
                  <l>Thou muſt Conſpire her death too?</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Beauf.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Hah! how's that, can that be true?</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mont.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> true, believe me Sir, and had not I,</l>
                  <l>Directed by her cries, come in by chance,</l>
                  <l>The Villain had accompliſht his deſign.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Beauf.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Heavens I is it poſſible?</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Damp.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Yes, employ'd by thee,</l>
                  <l>I would have been thy taſter <hi>Beaufort.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>I would have wanton'd with her, ſtroked, and tamed</l>
                  <l>The vertuous fool, then brought her gentle,</l>
                  <l>To thy longing arms.</l>
                  <l>Do'ſt thou not Love me for't? yes in thy heart</l>
                  <l>I know thou do'ſt, for who but I, would e're</l>
                  <l>Have taken ſo much pains to ſerve thy Luſt?</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Beauf.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Juſtly thou do'ſt reproach me <hi>Dampierre</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>We are both Villains, and on both I will</l>
                  <l>My ſelf ſee ſpeedy Juſtice done. Thou who</l>
                  <l>In ſpite of all my caution, haſt yet dipt</l>
                  <l>Thy hands in blood, ſhalt ſuffer death with the</l>
                  <l>Moſt cruel tortures our ſevereſt Laws</l>
                  <l>Inflict on murderers. As for my ſelf,</l>
                  <l>Here I renounce the world, and all its joys,</l>
                  <l>Reſolved henceforth in ſome Remote</l>
                  <l>And Unfrequented Hermitage to ſpend</l>
                  <l>The ſmall remainder of my wretched days</l>
                  <l>At Nature's charge: Where the cold clammy earth</l>
                  <l>Shall be my bed: homely, but wholeſome roots</l>
                  <l>My daily food, and water from the</l>
                  <pb n="52" facs="tcp:199141:31"/>
                  <l>Neareſt Spring my only drink. There on my</l>
                  <l>Bended knees I'll try to appeaſe the anger</l>
                  <l>Of offended Heaven, and with repeated</l>
                  <l>Earneſt vows ſolicit pardon for all my faults.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Damp</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Ha ha ha!</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Beauf.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Canſt thou laugh wretch?</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Damp.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Yes heartily, at thee and thy pretended penance.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Beauf.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Away with him, and load him well with Irons.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Damp.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Do thy worſt old man, I fear not thee, nor death.</l>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Damp.</hi> is led out</stage>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Beauf.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Now there is little left for me to do,</l>
                  <l>But to diſcharge my duty to the dead.</l>
                  <l>In ſad and ſolemn pomp I will attend</l>
                  <l>Them to the earth, and give them both one grave.</l>
                  <l>There, when in peace their dear lov<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>d Aſhes lie,</l>
                  <l>From Treacherous eaſe, from all vain joys i'll fly,</l>
                  <l>And tho I live, yet to the world i'll dye.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <trailer>FINIS</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <p>THe Inhuman Cardinal, or Innocence Betrayed. A Novel by Mrs. <hi>Mary Pix:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now in the Preſs and will ſuddenly be publiſhed, the ſecond part of the propoſal to the Ladies, wherein a Method is offered for the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provement of their minds. By the Author of the firſt part, 12<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. Printed for <hi>R. Wilkin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>OVid <hi>Traveſtie, or a Burleſque on</hi> Ovid'<hi>s Epiſtles; by Captain</hi> Ale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xander Radcliff, <hi>of</hi> Grayes-Inn.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Old Batchelor: A Comedy, by Mr.</hi> Congreve.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Family Phyſician, being a Choice Collection of the beſt Remedies for the Cure of all Diſeaſes incident to humane Bodies; very uſeful in Families, and ſerviceable to Country People. To which is added the true Engliſh Wine-Cellar, being the beſt method to make all Engliſh Wines, and Metheg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lin; with a Collection of the Choiceſt Coſmetick Remedies to preſerve the Complexion of Ladies<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Publiſhed by</hi> George Hartman <hi>Phylo-Chymiſt, and Servant to Sir</hi> Kenelm Digby <hi>till he Dyed.</hi> Price 2 s. 6 d. <hi>Printed for</hi> Richard Wellington, <hi>at the Lute in St.</hi> Paul'<hi>s Church-Yard.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:199141:31"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
